Truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Steven
Damick and Father Steven De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey, good evening, giant-
killers, dragon slayers, dragon tamers.
You are listening to Lord of Spirits podcast, my co-host.
Father Steven DeYoung is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I am Father Andrew Steven DeYoung in a Mayan's, Pennsylvania.
And we are live after a month of prerecords.
We are live again.
And if you are listening to us...
But not for long.
Oh, yeah.
That's true.
We're going to do another prerecord soon.
Hey, don't complain, you guys.
You can either have nothing or a prerecord.
Press me if I could stay home and just do life.
shows I would. Yeah, summer is the time we got to travel and stuff is just the way
there it is. So, but we are alive and you can call us at 855-237-2346 and you can
talk to us. We're going to get to your calls in the second half of the show and
our much beloved Matyska Trudy will be taking your calls. Tonight we're
going to be talking about the cheese sandwich oracle in the third half but first
in this episode.
is sponsored by the Orthodox Studies Institute at St. Constantine College, which exists to advance
the study and application of Orthodox Christianity in faithfulness to Holy Tradition. OSI is offering
online courses this fall, including a five week course on the Book of Enoch taught by our very
own Father Stephen D. Young. You can learn about the courses. That's true. That's right. You can
You can learn about the courses and register at orcthedocstudies.com.
dot com slash LOS, that's a special link for you, Lord of Spears listeners, orthodoxstudies.com slash LOS.
And if you register using that link, you will get a free copy of Father Stevens book, apocrypha, an ebook, a free ebook copy from ancient faith publisher.
And that's a free ebook that you can download without feeling vaguely guilty like you normally do.
That's right.
We know how you people are.
I'm sure the purpose is only book like books working man's out here trying to make a buck
You're off being bloody pirates. That's right
Petty Larsen all over the internet. I mean
I've tried see now I'm suddenly blanking on
The lead singer of Metallica
Not whatever James headfield. Yeah, no, not James headfield
That's the lead singer. That is who it is. Yeah, but yeah
I was thinking
back to the days of Kazaa and...
Oh, you're thinking about Lars Ulrich suing everybody?
That's right, Lars Ulrich suing everybody.
Yes, that's right.
Yes, anyways, the cheese sandwich Oracle
and other means of magical divination
because this is a special episode
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
And after Square we tell you not to do drugs kids.
don't do drugs.
an episode of the scurlessness of sorcery, the Mendacity of magic, the infamy of incantation,
the horror of the Haru specs, and the exocribleness of the ex-dispx. Any other literations we should
add to the list there? No, I'm glad you stuck the landing on the ex-dispx.
Ex-dispx. There at the end, yeah. Ex-dispx. It would be very easy to accidentally say etch-es-gech,
Right. That's true. Our Etch sketches some
of divination. Call in, let us know.
I suppose somebody could come to, like, you'd have to like half shake it. Like, you'd have
to draw something, shake it only slightly and then like, read the remaining.
Yeah.
Had her.
Yes.
Much like, you know, some Middle Eastern women do with upturned cups of Arabic coffee.
Yeah.
You could kind of do that with an Etruscatch.
Or one of those things.
What were those things called where they had like-
like the, it was a kind of black kind of rubbery plastic thing
and then there was like a plastic film over it
and you'd like right on it with a plastic pen.
Oh, yeah.
And like it would stick to the backing
and then you could like peel it up
and then it would be like blank again.
I know what you're talking about, but it's,
the 80s had all kinds of cool toys.
Yes, the crude science of the late 70s and early 80s.
Yeah, they're all cuz-
of like good high concept things, you know, like that.
Light bright.
Which unlocks the magic of colored light.
So, yeah, we've talked about magic before.
We've talked about magic before,
but we've never dedicated a whole episode to it.
So this is that episode, boys and girls.
Yes, this is magic in the ancient world,
not press to digitation or a sleight of hand,
or the lyingness of legit domain.
If you want that...
go watch the prestige. I've never seen it, but I'm told it's a very good film.
Okay. Well, I'm almost tempted to send you home. Well, I was just one.
I'll just do the show. So it's so is one big monologue for you anyway. So,
yeah. So go watch the prestige. That's right. It's Batman versus Wolverine and
their 19th century stage magick. No, wait. Maybe I have seen it. I don't
remember when it came out. No, I can look that up while you start your monologue.
Some people's children.
I know.
It's got David Bowie and it playing Nicola Tesla.
Like how can you not want to see this movie?
Oh, I have seen this movie.
Okay.
I have seen it.
Yeah.
Okay.
It's just, I mean it was 1990, yeah, well the, when was the movie, when did the movie come
out?
Let's see.
Oh, 2006.
I see that was, you know, a whole lifetime ago for some people.
You should go watch it again, but since you've seen it before, you could do that on your
own time.
It's not abstracting us here at the show.
Bye.
Right.
Okay.
Anyway.
Magic in the ancient world.
Yes.
Yes, actual magic that doesn't involve my cocaine, which is the correct way to pronounce
his name.
Yeah.
So, magic in the ancient world broad topic, because there's a bunch of sort of subcategories
of magic.
This isn't like...
Uh...
that's exactly like. Like, Dujas of Dragons magic, right, where you've got sort of schools
of magic and classes of spells. We're not talking about that really. But there are a variety
of phenomena that could be described in the ancient world really as sort of parariligious
the sense that it involves spiritual entities and sometimes even gods and goddesses.
But it's something that primarily takes place outside of the formal priesthood.
Those lines blur sometimes, especially the further you go back, the blurrier those lines
get between formal priesthood and magical practitioner.
But by the time you get to, for example, the Roman Empire, these are different kinds
categories. But so we're really talking about a whole bunch of different
pararoligious phenomena that we're grouping together. And so it's not so much,
here's the schools of magic as it is, here are the different types of phenomena
that we're grouping into this one big category. Yeah. Yeah.
and what justifies...
grouping them all together.
Right?
Is that that they're used by one class and use one type
of spell slots?
What justifies grouping them all together
is that there are overarching things we can say
about the character of all these phenomena
that unite them legitimately into this category.
And at the broadest level when we're talking about magic,
We're talking about the manipulation.
of spirits, right? So spiritual beings that have agency and personality. The manipulation
of them by way of certain techniques. And what's going to primarily distinguish between
the different types of phenomena that we talk about in this category is primarily going
to be differences of
technique. So these are all ways of interfacing with these spiritual beings, which are to some
degree outside the general nature of the sacrificial priesthood within these cultures.
Yeah, these are sort of like much more kind of occasional sort of things. It's not like the
regular sacrifices you be offering to gods are...
or whatever. Right. And because it's techniques, it's
technique, right? Because it's these different forms of
technique, it's not a role. So the priesthood is a role
than a person plays a within a social construct, right? It's
a role you play with regard to your society and your culture.
Whereas because this is a sort of technique, anyone who learns it, right?
Anyone who has access to this knowledge and to these techniques can then at least hypothetically practice it.
Can practice those techniques.
Which means it's not going to be limited in the same way.
and the places where you see the most overlap.
This is the real reason why there's so much overlap between the institutional priesthood
as we might call it and magical practitioners early on like in Sumeria or in very early
Egypt is because of the infinitesimal literacy rate.
Yeah.
If you don't, if you can't read, then you're not going to be doing this stuff probably
because you can't like read the spell books and stuff.
Right.
You don't have access to this knowledge.
Yeah.
Yeah, we're.
where education on any kind of broad basis is negligible,
where literacy rates are negligible,
where literacy is basically confined to
an institutional priesthood,
as it was, for example, in the Old Kingdom in Egypt,
then those are gonna be the only ones
who have access to sort of magical stuff,
right, to these kinds of secrets and techniques.
These also...
So in terms of the last episode, we went and did some review and revisiting of devil figures
we talked about as Zazel and therefore touched on the watcher story again from the Anachic
literature because this is why you see their things like sorcery in witchcraft and making
of potions and divination in their alongside like...
metallurgy. Yeah, this is all stuff that the watchers are granting to bad people. Yeah, this is all
sort of technique. This is a sort of spiritual technology, right? It's a learning of techniques.
And so this was then included in when the Amarites, for example, claim, right, the Amuru claim they
have the antideluvian knowledge. Some of that knowledge is these magical techniques, right, to
interface.
with spearbeings.
And also because it has that nature of technique,
of a procedure, that means that it also
is always gonna have to some extent a ritual nature.
Right, now when you think of magical ritual,
this doesn't mean you're always gonna have 50 people
in matching robes, right?
Wandering around in circles with torches, chanting something.
Right.
like it's not like in dark dungeons kids.
Right, right.
No, that's how D&D is.
That's exactly what it's like to play D&D at a frat house.
But otherwise completely inaccurate.
But ritual, I mean, an individual person,
a single person can engage in ritualized behavior.
Yeah, of course.
I mean, right, I'll do that.
every day. Yeah, one person can chant something, one person can make something, one person can draw
something, one print, right? You could, you could do the procedure, right? As a, as a solo practitioner.
So just saying ritual doesn't mean necessarily big elaborate. Hu ha, right out in the woods or
something. But so there are these ritual elements. There are material elements that get involved.
As we'll see as we talk about some of these
different types of
Magic. So the first one of these the first category sort of broad category we want to talk about is
Get a strike people as funny
Right off the bat
From a biblical perspective because they're not you're still thinking of it this way
But the first category is really signs and wonders a K a miracles
Yeah
Yeah, I mean, I think for Christians, we feel like a miracle is something different. It's something good and holy and from God.
And magic is dark and evil and demonic.
But is that how the ancient world would have seen it?
Right. Right.
And so,
Thamatergy,
Wonderworking, right, we have saints.
We're giving the title,
Thamateros, right?
Like, say, Nicholas,
Right, they're wonder-working safe.
They were Gregory the Wonder Woman. I mean, there's a bunch with titles like that. Yeah. Yeah. And we're not saying they're wizards
We're not saying they're miracle max right where
What
Desinates this when it is magic right when it is in the context of magic is the idea that
the practitioner the magical practitioner has
power or authority in a sense of the Greek word exocere, right? They have this power and authority that allows them to command spirits.
Yeah, it's not that they have some inherent ability. It's they can tell spirits to do a thing.
Although it's not really manipulating them, it's more like making them do a thing.
Right so it's not ingratiating yourselves to them or contacting them and asking them questions or
We'll talk about those other things.
Yeah.
This is commanding, right?
Now the key difference, right?
The key difference from the Jewish and Christian perspective
is that the prophets, right, and the apostles,
so those who worked wonders, worked miracles,
biblically, that was God acting through the person
to do the things.
Right.
It's not so much that the person is doing the thing,
is a-
that God is doing it and that person is simply the instrument of God.
Of course, Christ being God was doing the things, right?
Yes.
But even he, even he, you notice the way he talks about his miracles, like in St. John's Gospel,
right, that Christ says he's doing the Father's works.
Right.
Because he wants to make clear, we'll talk about this a little more in the second half,
Right, the accusation.
against him when he's working miracles is not that he's faking it by his opponents. Right.
Right. The accusation against him is regards whose authority and power he's using to do it. Yeah,
yeah, yeah. Right. And so that is why he always makes clear, right, that this is these are the
the works of God. But so that's that's one type and there are
We'll talk about this more in the context of the New Testament also, but even outside of that completely outside of that you can find in the ancient world plenty of
wonderworkers
and sorcerers and people who are supposed to be able to do this right
Apolognes of Tiana is the one that lots of
skeptical
New Testament types like to bring up because he was a rough contemporary of Jesus who was supposed to
have done a bunch of miracles.
Hmm.
And they think that's gonna be a big problem for us.
Right? It's like,
oh, Tarnit, Christianity all falls apart
because someone other than Jesus did a miracle?
What?
Yeah, but more on that in a moment.
Yeah, we'll get to that.
We'll get back to that.
But so that's one sort of category, right?
These figures who for whatever reason,
and there were different reasons why they said,
So some of them...
they would say, oh, they were basically partially
divine themselves.
And so that meant they had his power or authority
or they had just acquired the ability
to do it.
They had been empowered in some way
that they could do this.
They were just great sold.
And that allowed them to do this.
So they're always different ideas of...
why it was that someone could do that.
Right.
So then another category that falls under magic
is demonology.
Yeah, that's all those, I was gonna say
that's all those cartoons about people accidentally
summoning demons or deliberately summoning demons.
Yeah.
We'll get into the guy who inspired fouls later.
But so the analogy, right, or if we're doing any of the Greek,
demonology, right, is about the logos regarding spirits, right?
So the idea here is that this kind of magic involves a direct interaction
with spiritual forces, like with a spirit.
Yeah, like you're summoning them or you know their secret name or something like that.
And you can make them show up and you talk to them and manipulate them and make them do things.
Right. And so the kind of knowledge we're talking about here and the kind of texts we're talking about here
would be these sort of catalogs of different spirits.
what those spirits would do ways in which you could summon or manipulate them,
their names which you could use in some cases to get them to do certain things,
or to protect yourself from them. All of these kind of things fell into that category.
Right.
And so there are these sort of catalogs.
We'll see a lot of...
get to the third half we're going to be talking about sort of the legacy of this and how a lot of this stuff has stuck around in culture.
You can probably already think of ways in which that kind of thing stuck around.
But yeah, so that's what that's about. That's about dealing sort of directly with spirits.
um
the next category
one of the most popular categories. We're going to get to another category that's the actual most popular category but one very
major category in the ancient world. More major than those first two, right? Like
Wonderworkers, you get the occasional Wonderworker, right? It's not like every
village had a miracle guy. And you know, not every village had somebody who had
catalogued all of these local spirits. But almost every community in the
the ancient world had somebody who practiced divination.
in some way.
Yeah, which is this idea that you gain knowledge,
not just of the future, but it could be about the present
or even the past through some kind of spiritual means.
So information you wouldn't normally get,
you couldn't just learn.
You did some kind of technique, some spiritual technique
and that gave you the information.
That's a divination.
So we most of
think about that. Like you said in terms of the future, right? Like what's going to happen
in the future? Because I'm worried about it. You know, I'm about to go into battle.
Am I going to win? Right? Yeah, which is definitely a major piece of what ancient
diviners are doing. Yeah. Yeah. But there's also like in terms of the present,
right? You could think of people trying to make decisions in the present. What should I do?
or even
trying to find someone or something.
Right, where are they?
What are they doing?
Where are the bodies buried?
Yeah, where are the bodies?
Did I bury the bodies in a good place?
Yeah, that is a bigger issue in the ancient world
than you might have been people might have.
But that also the past.
Yeah, right.
also the past, right?
what happened to so and so, where did this come from?
And you see, for example, in Isaiah,
the God of Israel says, you know,
in comparing him to the other gods, you know,
go ahead and ask them about the things
that happened in the past,
or the things that will happen to the future, right?
Cause they don't know, right?
Cause they're not omniscient, right?
But so this
This takes a whole bunch of forms.
Yeah.
So one very popular one, especially among the Romans,
but all around popular was Agri, which is looking for omens.
Most popular watching the flights of birds.
Yes.
Lots of this type of bird flying in this direction at this time of day means X.
Yeah, which happens.
Like, if you read the Iliad,
Eagles going one direction or another
like, oh, Zeus is saying this, I get happens over and over in that book.
Yeah. Yeah.
There are birds of ill-Omen and not just Ravens perched upon your bust of Palace.
Nice.
But yeah.
So all these kinds of things, but it could be and you know, legacy stuff of that,
you know, black cat, right?
All these kind of things, right?
This is a sign, this is an Omen.
And so an auger was somebody who was adept at interpreting those things.
Right? I saw this in a dream. Right? What does it mean? Right?
And then very popular, especially in Rome, where the Senate had official ex-dispixes and
horospixes or horospices actually ex-dispaces.
Ex-dispacy, which was the reading of entrails of sacrifice of sacrificial animals.
You know, you know thinking about that. I mean, this is all over, of course, ancient literature,
particularly ancient Greek and Roman literature.
I always think to myself, who is the first guy who, you know, pulled the guts out of some
animal and said, ah, I see.
Well, it's a sacrificial animal. So you have to butcher it.
Right.
So it's probably the first guy who noticed something weird while he was butchering.
the animal. Oh yeah and maybe you know the king or whoever is like what is that? He's like oh that
means you will be victorious in battle. Yeah. There's a big black tumor in here. Yeah like yeah yeah.
Yeah and so there's some famous episodes too in Roman history right there's one where they killed
an animal and it didn't have a heart. Yeah yeah. And that was taken to be an omen of doom.
I don't like it.
They say that's functionally impossible.
Well, you know, things happen for your booksharing animals.
But yeah, so this was this was huge and we have from even earlier than that. So this goes back way before Rome.
We have like clay livers and splines like fired clay
with kuneiform inscriptions on them in different places that list different types of markings you can see in different places.
No, wow. So it's like those charts on your doctor's office wall.
Yeah.
It was like your guide too. So you take out the sheep's kidney, right? And you have this correctly sized and even mostly correctly colored sheep kidney
made a fired clay with
stamped into it in kineiform like oh if you see a marking here it means this if you see one over here it means this
to help your
newly minted
Exit of C's to get their
I guess they're feeders of them.
Species.
They're trying to learn the organs.
This also, though, divination also includes
Irracular activity, meaning like oracles, which was a form of possession by spirits.
The God or the Spirit takes over the body of the oracle and speaks through them.
Right, and can the end have superior knowledge to human
knowledge and can impart that. Oracle Delphi, for example, was supposed to be Apollo, who
was possessing the person and just had an ironic sense of humor as far as I can tell from
all of Greek literature. It's true. You never gave anyone a straight answer.
I know. You go to the Oracle Delphi and he says, ax, you're like, oh, I must avoid
ax. Spends the rest of his life avoiding ax and everything you did to avoid it is what
makes you land at X to the end.
Yeah.
Yes.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, so that's, but,
demons, they have a sense of dark sense of humor.
Not.
Yeah, but yeah, I mean this stuff,
again, if you read classical literature,
but even just the big ones,
like the early of the Odyssey, the Unid,
this stuff is everywhere there.
Like it happens so much, you get bored
and start wanting to skip it.
Right, it's really frequent.
It's like, it's really, yeah, it's exactly,
It's like-
people checking the news. That's what it is. It's that frequent.
You know, these are the news.
They're both the entrails of a sheep.
Yes.
Oh no, it's an eagle flying left.
Really glory, Twitter.
And then, relatedly, of course, you have the reading of all
kinds of other things.
Right.
Yes.
Yeah, the eventualities, right?
which leads us into the next category.
which is astrology.
And we've talked about astrology a little bit, especially in the back of the episode
where we talked about Jewish astrology and distinguished it from pagan astrology.
That pagan astrology has the same presupposition actually as Jewish astrology
that the celestial bodies are divine.
right as we talked about we won't do the long quote from
file log in because I think
We've done it four or five times in different episodes.
But follow up of Alexandria in talking about the difference
between these two types of astrology.
Talks about how pagan astrology,
they think that the Sun, Moon, and stars are gods
who have power in and of themselves to affect life
on earth.
Whereas in Jewish astrology,
they're understood to be,
He still uses the term ga-
we would use the term angelic beings probably because we're squeamish about that kind of thing.
And we prefer not to use biblical language for some reason.
Yes.
It gives us the heavie-jeebies.
So, meaning that they're sort of lower ranked members of God's divine administration,
but through whom he communicates.
So Jewish astrology was based around the idea that God communicates.
things to us through the stars. Right? And that's why there was no cognitive dissonance about the
Magi following the star to see Jesus from a Jewish perspective that was like, oh yeah God does that.
He communicates things through the right heavens declare the glory of God and all that. We talked
about that in that previous episode. But so in the pagan sense, right? This is where the magic comes
in. The pagan sense.
These are governing what is happening and going to happen on Earth.
And so being able to chart these things and find the patterns,
right, basically gives you another way to predict what is about to happen.
Yeah, I mean, it's sort of like, frankly, it's sort of like tracking the tides,
which literally are affected by the moon.
So it's the same concept, really, you know,
that there's this sort of influence being.
projected onto the people of the earth from all these heavenly bodies. But of course,
they don't have the cosmology we do. For them, the planets are in stars and so forth.
They're kind of much closer, much more directly relevant to our lives.
Yes. There's this presumed, which is a constant within paganism, is a presumed sort of fatalism.
Yes. Right. Meaning, you're destiny, your fate is pretty much written.
Yeah, right. And is controlled by these forces.
above and beyond you. And so that includes right the heavenly bodies. But here's
the thing we have to remember, right, even as we say that. Because when we hear
that today, right, what you might hear is, oh, they were like Calvinists, right? Just
with the feet.
or the Norns or something, being the ones instead of the divine decree. Right? And the problem there
is Calvinism is a form of modernism. It emerges in the early modern period. Meaning individualism
is baked into it. Right? I.E. for John Calvin, the God who created the universe cares about
individual people, at least some of them.
Yeah, whereas with pagans, the gods, don't care about anybody, right?
So there's some demigods, whatever they kind of fond of,
but they don't cry too long, even when one of them gets smelt.
Yeah, or a hero or something.
So, yeah.
If you're the average person,
Okay.
You wouldn't go to an astrologer and have them do your chart to tell you that you're going
to find love in the future.
Right.
Most of them are like, and you are.
Yeah, the stars of the planet don't care about you finding love.
Okay.
That whole thing wasn't even a category.
You were already married at age 13.
You didn't get to go fall in love.
Well, I mean, in many parts of the ancient world love was a sickness that you could get the
doctor to come and cure you of.
You've already got love at home and then there's a picture of your love at home
But
It wasn't like that right so they're doing this stuff. This is stuff like think of the bad guy right a great king has been born
This is the kind of stuff where
Working with like the rise and fall of civilizations at least cities right we're tired these huge things right now
These huge happenings obviously affected normal people
Sure.
Right.
But the fact that they didn't directly control or involve those normal people kind of gave
those normal people some wiggle room in terms of that fatalism.
Right.
Like, hey, your city's going to be overrun by invaders from the east.
Okay.
Time to move west.
Right?
Like you could hypothetically.
If you were able to get a hold of this knowledge of what's going on, you could plant.
That's why you would have kings, other people would have advisors who were astrologers,
so that they could be warned of what was going to make preparation.
Or just warned in terms of now's not the time to go to war.
kind of things. But so even while on the one hand
This presumes a kind of fatalism that these outside forces are controlling what's going to happen.
The fact that you can chart it and map it out and inform someone of it gives some wiggle room to that fatalism.
So there's a tension there all the time.
Right.
And ultimately the more important you were, the more doomed you were.
So lots of reasons not to want to be important in the ancient world.
So then.
Probably the most popular form of this magic is actually alchemy, but this is alchemy
more broadly considered than you're probably used to thinking about it.
If you spend a lot of time thinking about alchemy, that hey, if you do, cool, I guess?
A little weirder than the people who apparently think about the Roman Empire every day.
I do think about the Roman Empire every day.
Are they good thoughts or are they bad thoughts?
Depends, depends on the day, depends on the context, but pretty much this is my life.
Like at some point every day the Roman Empire comes up for me.
But yeah, Alchemy's a little weirder.
So alchemy, probably so part of the issue with magic is
is that we've been sort of taught to think of magic
as primitive science.
Right.
This is one of those modernism things again,
because if you're a good modernist,
science will solve all of our problems.
Science can answer every question.
Science can be applied to any field
of human activity.
All of which is ridiculous, right?
I mean, all the science is very good at certain things.
It useless for everything else.
But if you're a good modernist, everything is science.
And therefore, think about our 19th century German friends.
We have our evolutionary trail, right?
Humans trying to figure things out starts with primitive dirt, right?
And it ends up with science.
It's up with 19th century German science, right?
which is the pinnacle of all human inquiry.
And so alchemy for example, well alchemy is a primitive form of chemistry.
Yeah, that's how it's seen.
Yeah, or astrology is a primitive form of astronomy.
Right.
And now we have like the real version and not your bogus goofy unscientific version.
Now we have all the science I don't understand. It's just my job five days a week.
Yeah.
So, this is wrong.
That's magic at all of these things are actually doing something different.
Right?
So, astronomy is fundamentally trying to do something different than what astrology was trying
to do.
Yeah, I mean, in a sense, a strong...
is sort of like the bookkeeping of astrology early on anyway.
Yeah, yeah.
But it's fundamentally different questions being asked
and being asked in a different way.
And the same thing with Alchemy and chemistry.
Right.
So these aren't at end.
Yes, I know, side 5A.
any sufficiently advanced science is indistinguishable from magic.
Which again is this hypothesis that if magic works, it can't actually be magic.
It has to be some kind of science.
Just has to be some science we haven't figured out yet.
Science is everything. Science explains everything.
does everything. But anyway, so what are we talking about? We're actually talking about alchemy.
Well, we're actually talking about the production of objects and substances.
Yeah, sort of power in a thing.
Right. That will allow you to manipulate spiritual forces.
So, if you're here, Alchemy, you might think, oh, well, they were trying to figure out how to turn
lead into gold. That's one thing. Right. But how are they going to try to do that?
They're going to try to do that using the philosopher's stone.
Right.
So that's an object that you create.
And if you create it, then this object will give you this power over the material order.
Right.
But this also includes things like making potions.
Love potion number nine was a real thing.
I don't know what happened to love potions.
one through eight. There were probably horrible failures that
distributed people. I don't know. The songs about those were very, very different.
Yes. But love potions actually were very common in the ancient world. And we're
using love there euphemistically. Right. So that's what potions as it were.
Yes. Love potions in the sense of, you know, Rohit Nal. Right. This is basically
But that's a substance, right? It wasn't just that. There were of course things that were supposed to make you healthy or make you younger, right? At least make you look that way.
All these sort of things. But these were seen to be manipulating spiritual forces to do this through tinctures and different combinations of things.
Farma Kea is also under this. It's often translated sorcery, but primarily that's
related to like hallucinogens, which were discovered very early. And hallucinogens were
used to enter into the spiritual world, to enter into the world of dreams and interact
there with spiritual beings that they didn't call machine elves at the time because they
didn't have machines or else but probably the same
little dudes. And then amulets, which were probably the most common. If you
want the number one most common magical thing, magical practice of the ancient
world, it was amulets, which includes pendants, rings, other talismans you could
wear on your body. And those would either ward off some
spirit that you want it warded off or caused some spirit to protect you from
something else like arrows, right? Like if you were going into battle. And the
idea was one of the most common ones in the Greek and Roman worlds were
Medusa faces. They not only be worn but they put them for example on shields.
on armor when going into battle. And Medusa was a priestess, and we all know what priestess
is a euphemism for in the ancient world, who was apparently incredibly beautiful, and
a couple of goddesses got jealous of her. And so they cursed her, it gave her snakes
for hair, and made her hideous.
Yeah, I mean there's various versions of that another one is that yeah
She gets raped and punished for being raped.
That gets really awful.
Yes.
So pretty horrible.
So it's like, well, why would you put her face on things?
Obviously, it wasn't turning people to stone in and of itself.
Well, the idea was that the image of her misfortune,
or sort of ultimate misfortune from the gods,
would ward off misfortune from you.
Yeah.
sort of like trying to put the same poles
of a magnet together.
Sort of push bad things away from you
through the image of bad things.
Sort of the, I think it's sort of
some of the same theory behind gargoyles actually.
I don't know.
There's a lot of weird theories about gargoyles,
but that's what they put producer heads on buildings too.
Yeah, oh yeah.
Yeah.
But, and this was...
constant in the ancient world.
Tons of this.
We have these amulets everywhere in archaeological finds.
But also this was one of the hardest things to sort of fight against in Jewish and Christian
communities.
We'll talk more about that later.
But sort of no, you don't need to wear this thing to protect you, you're a Christian,
right?
Christ does that.
live faithfully.
Right God protects you. You don't you don't need this you don't need the whammy
But my just personal favorite because I think it's cool
Sort of magical object the ancient world where execution bowls
Right which
Execution boys and girls is not what you're thinking
It's no, it's a curse. Yes, it's curse. It's cursing. Yeah, yes
And you should really, you know,
when you find something really abhorrent,
you should really say it's exocurable.
Yes.
It's nice to have saying a curse.
They're on to us, I hear about anathema.
Oh.
They figured out what that means.
So now we'll have to use exocurable.
Exocration?
No.
A bowl of exocoration.
But, if they should bowl...
You would make a piece of clay pottery, right?
Usually a bowl.
A whole bowl of clay.
And you would put someone's name, right?
And some kind of curse.
You would write in the clay before it was fired.
And then after it was fired, you would read it and then smash it on the ground to symbolize
sort of cursing and smashing that person.
Now I do not recommend you do this.
Because it is a very bad thing to do and you don't need to be cursing people and somebody's
got to clean that up.
Potchards are very sharp, so we can get hurt.
But it's just sort of cool and dramatic.
Yeah.
In terms of the ancient world.
So those are sort of our broad categories.
Right. And there's lots of other, I mean, it's not like this is these are the category, right?
There's lots of ways you could categorize things, you could move things around.
You can put things together, right? But that's sort of a brief survey of the kinds of phenomena
we're talking about when we're talking about magic in the ancient world.
So we say something about who the practitioners were.
Yeah, who actually did this stuff?
Yeah, and as I mentioned when you go back very
early. This is confined to your literate class, especially early on, and so that means it's
combined mainly to your sort of, not even your whole priesthood, like a subset of your religious
priesthood that are lecters, right? Do do how to read, who are literate. And if I have access to
ancient tablets and scrolls and that kind of thing. But as it develops, you get sort of
You
official magical practitioners, what we might call official
practitioners and then unofficial practitioners.
And this isn't official and unofficial like dragon age or
something or dragon lance.
It's not like you had to have a license to practice magic, right?
Or like, right.
Only these people are allowed to do it.
You people are not.
That's not what we mean by official and unofficial.
It's more sort of like ruling.
class and not ruling class or formal and informal even.
Right.
Yeah.
So when we talk about official,
practical, magical practitioners,
we're talking about essentially institutions
that develop around this.
You see, you're talking about people who are parts
of royal or imperial courts,
who practice these things, right?
Court astrologers, court magicians,
uh...
Like I mentioned the Senate had official horospices.
And if you are, this actually comes up at one point
in the book of Acts.
We won't go into detail right now about it,
but in the book of Acts it actually comes up at one point
that because like local governors,
procurewators in the Roman Empire,
didn't have access to the Senate's official horospices
or exorcises.
And so they
had to try and employ locals to do their divination at
augury because the official guy's only worked for the
the Senate, the emperor, right? And a few other people in
the Patricia glass. So a pro consul would have to like
either ask his consul like, hey, can you get the official
guy to look at some spleen for me? So I get a little
Um.
But so that tells you when we say official that tells you like just how institutionalized it was
Yeah, right this was completely normal. This is not weird things that people did out in a shack in the bayou
Right, this is yeah, this is
You know the the in the Imperial Court or the King's Court
Right, there's priests
There's patricians right noble people wealthy people
There's you know.
poets and singers, there's cooks, there's people who practice different types of magic for the king or emperor.
That's just how it was. It was a very institutionalized thing. It was a department essentially that took care of that.
Okay, so then when we're talking about unofficial, we're talking about people who don't occupy
those kind of official institutional positions.
Yeah.
It might be the person that shacked out in the buy you, but it also might be
somebody you go and pay some money to do this job for you.
So there were people who did this for hire,
either on a traveling basis, they kind of bummed around and did this,
knew how to practice some form of something of this,
help you find where to dig the well.
right, let's tell you the augers right
tell you what the Omen's mean, this kind of thing. And there were people who would just become known for doing it.
Yeah. Right. You'd read a few Omen's and whatever you said would actually be right and happen. And so you get this reputation and so people from the neighboring villages and stuff would come see you where they had questions and pay you something.
To tell them, right.
And then there were also just people who didn't even take money.
Just, you know, there's...
some old woman in the village, who knows how to do something.
Notice how to make some poultice that'll make
the guy your eyeballing, decide to sleep with you.
Just sort of very informal, sort of practitioners
of various forms of this,
or who knew how to make amulets,
would make amulets for people in the village,
or that kind of thing.
So we can get very, very...
informal. And again, there was no like rule against it. Like, oh, no, you can't. Again,
this is, I know this runs counter to a lot of people's narratives, right? Like, you know,
oh, no, these wise women were persecuted by all the men who know that it was fine, no one cared.
This was, that's like, you know, who let her cook with potatoes, right? Like, this was,
That's how common a lot of these magical practices were in the ancient world.
It was not seeing as some kind of big deal.
It was part of their life.
Everybody did it.
It's just like the way we treat,
frankly, the way we treat medicine today.
Yeah.
And I'm not saying this is primitive medicine.
I'm just saying it occupies basically
the same kind of place.
Like if you've got the money in the power,
you can go to the big doctors, you know.
at the famous university hospitals.
You know, a lot of people are going to urgent care
and a lot of times, you know, your mom just puts a bandaid on you.
Like, this is the level where it's sort of pervasive
everywhere in society.
You're telling.
Your dad dumps whiskey in the wound to,
yeah, yeah, and folk remedies and stuff.
Yeah, yeah.
Or if you think about nutrition and health.
Right.
Yep, you know.
Everybody's doing it and everybody believes somebody in the family who's like no here's the way you need to eat this
You know, then you'll feel better. You lose weight, you know, yeah
Yep exactly
All right, well, that's the first half of this episode on the
cheese sandwich oracle
We're gonna take a deal of bread and cheese. It's like Arto Tiro mancy. Yes, Arto Tiro mancy. Yes. We'll be right back
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and father
First even to young will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the
Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
The top ten reasons to attend the ancient faith men's retreat.
Number one, fellowship with other Orthodox Christian men.
Number 2. Hearing from 4 speakers, all.
priests and one high-remunk.
Number three, Daily Matins and Besper's,
plus Acatist on Friday and Divine Liturgy on Sunday.
Number four, supplication at the relics of St. Raphael
and learning about his life in the Antiochian Village Museum.
Number five, giving back to Antiochian Village
to a service project.
Number six, enjoying the beautiful grounds
of Antiochian Village, including the meditation trail
in Hikes.
Number 7.
Football during free time.
8. Delicious Breakfast Lunch and Dinner
9. Bonfires and Smoors Each Night
10. The Opportunity to Learn and Be Encouraged
In What It Means to Be a Man
August 22nd through the 25th, 2024 at Antiochian Village in Bolivar, Pennsylvania.
For more information and to register, just click on the banner on the Ancient Faith website
homepage or the lead graphic on the AFM app.
We really hope to see you there!
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back everybody.
You know, no D&D tournament?
I know.
What kind of a conference is this anyway?
What?
I mean, I always think it shouldn't top 10 lists.
Shouldn't they be again reverse order?
Should you like start with number 10 and go to number one?
Yeah, you should go 10 to one.
That is a mistake.
Also, I gotta say, not a smores guy.
The marshmallow.
Yeah.
I think marshmallows are kind of garbage.
I'm kind of anti-marshmallow.
But let me tell you this.
Here's the secret from Father Steven's House of Cheapness,
which I started doing with
I was broke. If you want to have a really delicious treat that is super cheap. Here's what you do.
You go and you buy yourself a box of generic graham crackers and then you go and buy yourself
a little tub of generic cake frosting and you make yourself sandwich cookies.
You have like days worth of sandwich cookies right there and it costs almost nothing.
Some of that ancient Dutch wisdom that you're passing on to us.
Yes.
Try it.
I'm telling you.
Yeah.
If you've got kids, right?
Like way cheaper than cookies.
It's true.
Absolutely true.
Yeah.
So.
Yep.
Well, hey, we're actually, we are, I was just saying we're getting a call in and I have
No idea actually what this, because truth is still typing out what exactly.
Is it on the phone or are you just receiving something man? No net. Oh, I just read my I'm receiving something right now
No, this actually this is Joseph whose phone is from Kentucky and he's calling about the oom and thumem I
knew someone was gonna ask about this
So Joseph, are they asking about both I've never had a question about the room
Welcome Joseph to Lord of Spheres podcast
How are you this evening?
I'm doing great. Thank you, fellas.
That's good.
So I was curious related to the Uraman Bumum.
I know, you know, obviously that's something that God told the Israelites to do in the Old Testament.
But like on a surface level it almost seems like divination.
So like how do you differentiate things like that from, I guess, divination proper?
Is it just the fact that God had them do it?
You
Yeah, I mean it's a kind of mysterious object that I will say do not involve putting your face in your hat
As far as you know
It's not in the Bible father. It's not a little test of it high priest wore a bowler hat. No
Or special glasses
Yeah, what is what is up with or a man through a second ever remember if it's umimen through him or or a man
Or even thumb them.
Yeah.
What is...
up with that. Is it divination? And by the way guys, if anybody out there has twins,
name them, Irrimanthumem. I mean, come on, it's right there. It's biblical.
But then you have to wear it on your breastplate. You can call one of them Yuri. You can call
the other one Phumem, I guess. I don't mean. What will we get the shorter end of the stick
there? Yeah. Nice. So I'm sorry. I just have to recognize that pun. Okay. Yes. What is
up with Orman Thumem.
And this is actually a good segue.
So the reason the Euroman Thumum are given
is precisely to try to stop
the Israelites from doing divination.
And so there's sort of this whole process outlined in the Torah
of how to determine God's will in terms of what they should do.
and sort of...
And then the last guest said, okay, we've done this whole process.
We've asked everybody we're supposed to ask, we've prayed, we've done this, we've done
all the things.
There were still not sure.
Right?
Then God says, okay, then throw the urban thovam.
We still don't know exactly how that worked.
Yeah, because it doesn't tell us.
Precise of the productions.
There was some way to do that that would then give...
the answer. And so the idea was it was sort of an accommodation to human weakness in being able to
figure these things out. But God saying okay when you get to that point you're still confused don't go and
start doing any of this other stuff that the nations are doing here do this. Right. And so I would say the
The reason we don't see anything similar to that.
in the church is that part of what the Holy Spirit does in terms of not just the
leadership structures of the church but the church as a whole is right right
the Torah on our heart right give us the wisdom of God so that we can figure
things out and we don't have to resort to that.
Yeah and I mean like the only thing I would say within the church that's remotely
similar as you get. I mean there's some
casting lots, but it's now it's mainly survives.
Like there's a handful of bishops
where casting lots can be an element of it
after a series of votes and whatever,
sometimes you'll get then, okay,
we'll put the three names into a chalice
and someone will pick out the name, you know,
that kind of thing, but that's not,
that's not the same thing as divination.
Right, and that's that again,
That's the last step, like we've tried.
all the ways we normally do this.
Yeah.
For whatever reason this time, we just can't figure it out.
So, okay.
Yeah.
This is sort of a way of letting God make the decision, right?
Rather than trying to discern something written somewhere else and manipulate it.
Right.
Yep.
So does that answer your question, Joseph?
It does.
Thank you, fathers.
All right.
I'm glad someone actually called in about that because we didn't actually have it in our notes to discuss believe it or not ladies and gentlemen
But you know we we trusted you we didn't have to divine that you would come up with that question
My just trusted one of you to call about it my notes are also just a bizarre series of words and phrases disconnected from anything
So yes, brother and
It's right to render them intelligible at least to himself. That's right
We have to spend hours, hours for me to decipher them.
I throw the urmin through him over and over again.
It's trying to-
What does he mean?
Existency?
What is this cheese sandwich thing all about?
No.
I think people don't think there's gonna be a payoff
with the cheese sandwich oracle,
but they're will, folks, they're will be
as this is a real thing.
It's a real thing.
I didn't believe it was a real thing until this morning
and now I know.
Now I know.
that doggies half the battle.
So, yeah. So this half, our second half of three, we're going to sort of talk about places
where magic and magical practices and this kind of thing show up in the scriptures. There
interesting things here along the way but I don't think
anything shocking in the sense that yes your oppression is correct when it comes to magic
the Bible's again it. Yes, yes spoiler alert. So in broadcatter there might be some interesting
things on the way here though. They're very going through there. So probably probably the
most famous reference to magic and magical practitioners in the Bible is Exodus 2218.
Yes, and you end...
Folks, you cannot beat the King James version of this verse.
Valchell not permit a witch to live.
So not suffer.
Is it suffering?
I'm sorry.
Valchell not suffer a witch to live.
I'm looking at the ESV.
That's not suffer a witch to live.
Yes.
In one lame translation, a female practitioner of sorcery.
Who could go for a sorceress?
Yeah.
What?
Wow.
Well, maybe they were a he-man fan and they didn't want to say say anything bad about the sorceress.
Oh, that seems logical.
He said, I's bird lady.
I miss the Facebook page Skellator is love.
There's one of the great Cobra Commander Twitter account.
Oh, really?
Yes.
Where he just always posts in character as Cobra Commander.
Oh, I mean, I'm a Twitter quitter, but I do occasionally look.
Yeah, I, I, on Twitter at all.
than what's in a while looking to see what co-worker band is up to.
I'm still holding out for your all professional wrestling Twitter account.
It may happen.
Right.
So just my musings on pressure, don't distract me with that now.
That's not so not suffer a witch talk about Rhea Ripley coming back on raw on Monday.
Then what are we going to do?
Anyway.
So yeah, well you don't suffer a witch to live.
And that is that line comes within a whole set of commandments about pagan sacrifice,
pagan ritual.
We won't go into detail, especially because of what the next verse says, but everyone's
going and looking it up now, because I said that.
But anyway, wait, what does it say?
It's all within this context of pagan worship and pagan practice that they're not
to do, right? Because of course Exodus is in the process there, chapter 22 of
laying out what their religious practice in Israel is going to be. So this is
instead of your, these are the things you're not going to do here and now or the
things you're going to do. Then we get a little more detail than at least in
in terms of a list of magical phenomena that are to be issued in
Deuteronomy 18.
Yeah, yeah, so Deuteronomy 18 I'm gonna read verses 9 through 14
When you come into the land that the Lord your God is giving you
You shall not learn to follow the abominable practices of those nations
There should not be a found you found among you anyone who burns his son or his daughter as an offering
anyone who practices
Divination or tells fortunes or interprets omens or a sorcerer or a charmer or a medium.
or a necromancer or one who inquires of the dead,
for whoever does these things is an abomination to the Lord.
And because of these abominations,
the Lord your God is driving them out before you.
You shall be blameless before the Lord your God
for these nations, which you are about to dispose us.
Listen to fortune tellers and to diviners.
But as for you, the Lord your God
has not allowed you to do this.
Right.
It's worth noting, right?
Again, we have to clear the modernism out of our heads a little.
Right?
God isn't telling them not to do these things because they don't work.
Right.
He's not telling you not to do these things because they're nonsense and a waste of time.
Right?
He's telling them not to do this because it works.
Yeah.
It's just like when St. Paul says, don't eat pagan sacrifices because it puts you into
communing with demons.
Yes.
And let me just a note to some of our Protestant friends,
probably none of the ones listening
because these folks wouldn't listen
to this show for this long.
But, you know, those of you out there
who like to call me a Necromancer.
First of all, that would be awesome.
I would have the coolest army of skeletons, right?
Like, if I actually were a Necromancer.
Alas.
I have not a single animate skeleton.
And the tower will go door.
So on one hand, we have, for example, what's in the Odyssey where you go and you sacrifice
a black goat and pour its blood into a trench and the spirits of the dead come up out of
Hades and drink the blood.
Okay.
Actually, Necromancy.
On the other hand, you have me asking St. Stephen to pray for me.
Right.
Yeah.
You're not gonna could be
It's been to me that you don't see the difference
between those two pictures.
Right, I mean, Necromancy is literally about using magic
to manipulate the dead to tell you the future and stuff.
Yes, you're not gonna, you can tell the difference
between those two pictures, don't lie.
Okay, you know the difference between these two things.
Yeah, I mean, and someone standing at the grave
of one of their dead family and saying,
I miss you, is not practicing Necromancy.
Now,
No.
And that's the thing.
And you were ritual to try to return them to life.
Yes, they are doing that.
Yes, right.
Exactly.
Yeah.
I mean, inquiring of the dead is not simply speaking with the departed.
It's about this.
It's about this sort of ritual manipulation of the spirits of dead people to get what you
want.
So your child to a hag to get a wand to bring your husband back as a zombie?
Just to choose a random example.
Many such cases.
Okay.
Yeah, so that's decaromancey.
Don't call me an acrobatist unless I get my army of skeletons.
That's the other piece of this.
So yeah, so all of this is forbidden to Israel.
But this is also one of those things where...
So we've talked about how to read the Bible.
than how to and not to read the Bible episode. We talked a little bit about the problem of
right the whole in the parts. Yeah. Right to understand the whole, you have to understand all
the parts, but to understand any of the parts, you kind of have to have an understanding of the whole.
Yeah. And so you have kind of this loop. But this is a case where a lot of times in the Bible,
we read the Bible in sort of these chunks, these thematic chunks. And our English Bibles
help us
do this by putting in those subheadings and dividing it into chunks for us.
Right? But just ing that it was written that way. Yeah, which it won. Right. And so often when you read
larger sections, certain things become clear because what Father Andrew read ended with verse 14 of
We'll do the run of the 18.
But then what comes next, in verse 15 and following, is not unrelated.
Yeah, follows right on.
So I'm going to read verses 15 through 22.
The Lord your God will raise up for you a prophet like me from among you, from your brothers.
It is to him you shall listen.
Just as you desire the Lord your God at horub on the day of the assembly, when you said,
let me not hear again the voice of the Lord my God or see His great fire anymore, lest I die.
The Lord said to me they are right and
what they have spoken, I will raise up for them a prophet like you from among their brothers
and I will put my words in his mouth and he shall speak to them all that I command him.
And whoever will not listen to my word that he shall speak in my name, I myself will require
it of him.
But the prophet who presumes to speak a word in my name that I have not commanded him to
speak or who speaks in the name of other gods, that same prophet shall die.
And if you say in your heart, how may we know that the word that the Lord has not spoken
when a prophet speaks in the name of...
the Lord if the Word does not come to pass or come true, that is a word that the Lord
has not spoken. The prophet is spoken it presumptuously. You need not be afraid of him.
Of course, it says earlier, that same prophet shall die. Yeah. And why be afraid of his
corpse? Right. So that's an echo me answer around. So, right, so this comes right afterward.
So the reason...
that they are not to engage in any of those practices,
is that God is going to send them a prophet.
Yeah, they don't need to do that.
Like to do that other stuff.
They're going to have a leader.
A guy like Moses.
Do we somebody who sits in Moses's seat, right?
Who is going to be there to adjudicate things for them,
to give them advice, to declare God's word
and God's will to them, right?
And they're to follow that person.
Yeah, and it's God saying like, look,
I'm-
offering you a pretty direct relationship with me,
with the divine.
Right.
It would be more direct,
but you guys didn't want that direct.
Yeah, right.
You guys got scared when I tried to do that.
Yeah, so I'm not gonna have to pick one guy, you know.
But like versus a sort of manipulative around the edges,
let me monkey with it myself thing,
which is what magic is all about.
Right, right.
So on the one hand,
they have to submit to an authority, which...
Yeah.
A lot of folks don't want to do.
But on the other hand, right, this isn't this person who has no accountability.
Right. Getting the prophecy thing wrong once and getting stoned to death.
That's accountability, right? Right. And it's it also kind of might make some people hesitate to take up the mantle.
Yes. Yes. If they weren't really called by God to do it.
Yeah, it's almost like all those saints
who didn't want to be made bishops, right?
Like they knew something was going on.
Yeah.
How about that?
Right?
So that's the balance, right?
That's the balance is this person
has the ultimate accountability before God.
This carries over.
St. Paul talks about this when he's
talking about leaders in the church
of the pastoral epistles, right?
How they receive a stricter judgment.
Not many of you should presume to be teachers, right?
which every time you try to start a-
Sunday school. Everybody quotes that back to you. But because there is this more serious
judgment for them, there is that accountability there. But on the other side, then, the
people are called to obey that accountable authority, right, as the person sent by God, right,
to lead them rather than trying to go out and voodoo this stuff sort of on their own
and I do have to put it in no-
sorry charismatic friends okay but I think we talked about this a little back in
the prophet mode of episode but I gotta say it again because I've heard it
recently again in some charismatic circles if you're gonna claim you're
hearing prophecies from God you're not allowed to get them wrong yeah you're
especially not allowed to get them wrong most of the time.
Getting them wrong most of the time then you're taking ideas that occur to you
And blaming God for them. I talked about this last time
God is not a liar
God doesn't get things wrong
Okay, so let's just call our own ideas our own ideas
Right and then if the idea turns out to be a brilliant idea that bears a lot of fruit then give God the credit for it
I'm right there with you
But don't jump the gun.
Right. Don't jump the gun.
This argument that somehow prophecy now works worse in the new covenant than it did in the old covenant.
It makes no sense.
Like everything in the new covenant is elevated,
superior to the old covenant.
That's the whole idea of the new covenant.
And you're saying, well, yeah, except prophecy now is like, can I miss?
Not how that works.
Okay, so let's just call our ideas, our ideas,
and like I said, if they bear fruit, then give God the credit,
give God the glory for it.
Then we'll all be happy.
And you won't feel dumb.
Right? I know there's a whole bunch of people.
Right? Just chomping at the bit, hoping that this current
election goes in a certain way so they could claim their
four years ago weren't actually wrong.
I know there's a bunch of them.
I have to say though, I love how every election,
one of the candidates is the Lord's anointed
and another one is the Antichrist
and then it all fades away and they're off the map
and suddenly the Antichrist isn't that important anymore
and the Lord's anointed wasn't that big of a deal.
There's no exit strategy for these pronouncements.
Yeah.
And I don't know.
I think the current version of the Antichrist,
you need a necromancer to be able to get it
to do anything all that evil.
But anyway.
We'll leave it to the reader as to who that might be.
Oh, I think we can figure out.
So, yeah, so we went into the profit mode of episode.
We talked a lot about Baylam, a son of Bayor.
You can go back there, but just refer to him here.
He's an example of one of those practitioners for higher.
A profit for higher, a profit for profit, as it were,
a for-profit profit.
Speaking of tax exempt status.
And we know that because he of course gets hired to go and curse Israel.
And this is apparently a thing, a thing that he does.
Probably the most famous, at least in the Old Testament, episode of magic or sorcery
or witchcraft is of course the witch of endor.
Uh...
uh...
Father Andrew...
it out of the ball. I was waiting for him to do the Ewok joke.
I don't know. I'm still, you know, traumatized. No, just kidding.
Yes, the Witch of Endor. Necromancers get armies of skeletons, but the Witch of Endor.
I don't blame you for experiencing trauma thinking about the election.
Are we the Ewoks?
Well, you know, whenever our commenters on YouTube just endorsed a Verman Supreme,
Well, that's fair. Yeah, I want my pony. Yeah.
pony based economy.
Yeah.
That's...
Um...
So the...
mandated teeth brushing?
Yeah?
I mean these are important issues.
I don't know. I don't know.
I might be too libertarian to vote for them on that tooth brushing thing.
And I'm not a libertarian, but just, you know, you can't tell me...
what to do.
Anyway, uh...
Who insidify? My army of skeletons?
as an echo answer or an army of Ewoks.
Wow.
Right now, someone is setting up a totally accurate battle
simulator scenario.
Yes.
Send us that video of skeletons versus Ewoks.
Skeletons versus Skeleton Army versus Ewoks.
I want that video people.
Yeah, I think I give it to the skeletons.
Here's why you walks primarily you spears piercing weapons no good against skeleton. Oh, that is true
Oh, but they do have some siege weapon type things like there is the logs that slam together
That's true. That's true. Yeah, so we have to take terrain and preparation into account. Yeah, yep. Yeah
But anyway, just better than for Jimmy McMillan
is not what that's his name right Jimmy McMillan
The one who talks about the rent. Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, I don't know if he's running this year
I actually signed up to be an electric for a third anyway
I'm not gonna say who
That only says and I actually signed up to be an electric for a third party candidate who's not gonna win
Just because I want to try and get out a zoom call with the candidate in question
Please film that
Anyway.
which of Endor who actually does engage in some necromancy but no army of skeletons.
Yeah, actual necromancy.
Yeah.
Magic.
So this is an interesting story because if you again, if you read the whole story of the
context, right, this is Saul's life is circling the drain at this point.
Right.
Yeah.
The Holy Spirit has left him.
Yeah, he's got an-
unholy spirit now hanging out with him. Tormenting him, he kind of had Samuel the
prophet to kind of rely on even though most of what Samuel told him was bad news.
Especially there at the end, but Samuel dies.
And so he decides he's going to resort to divination regarding the battle he's about to go into.
Because he sort of plagued, he thinks he's going to die. Spoiler's he is.
Right, but so he says, okay, I'm gonna go find a diviner.
I'm gonna go find somebody to do this for me.
And then he has a basic problem, which is he killed all the
magical practitioners, at least in the territory of
Benjamin and Judah.
So he had to go find one.
And then there's in for Samuel 28, where sort of the
encounter unfolds.
when she sees him she sort of.
freaks out because like oh yeah you went killed everybody else who did this. But then he convinces
her and she decides to do her thing which is a form of divination via sort of demonology, summoning
up spirits from the underworld to give her knowledge, right? In this case of what's going to happen
of the battle that
Saul is about to engage in, instead Samuel shows up in person and tells Saul that he and his
whole family are doomed.
Doomed.
Yeah.
But notice, even in this case, even in this case, remember what we talked about with Wiggle
Room?
What could Saul have done right there then?
Repent it.
Yeah, he could have said, stop, stop.
I'm sorry, prophet Samuel.
Yes, he could have repented.
Yeah, right.
But of course, he did.
Right, he did.
Speaking of repentance, a better example.
Manasseh.
Yes.
Before he repented.
Yes, this is before he repented.
This is what he had to repent of.
Right, this is why you're repenting.
You may...
the prayer of Manasseh if you went to
Great compliment during Lent.
Yeah, yeah. So second Chronicles chapter 33 versus 5 and 6.
And he built altars for all the hosts of heaven in the two courts of the house of the lord.
So it's star worship by the way everybody. And he burned his sons as an offering in the valley of
the sun of Hinam and used fortune telling and omens and sorcery and dealt with mediums and
end with
necromancers, he did much evil in the sight of the Lord, provoking him to anger.
It's pretty bad.
And I mean, you remember when he released his, his midget medium and there was a small
medium at large.
I think midget is a politically correct term now.
Oh.
See, I'm going to get canceled now.
I think you should have said dwarf
Yeah, you're the live on the show man. Why am I having to tell you?
That's what the kids say. I've got you trapped man because you're totally based. You have no choice.
I will. You're trying to be based. You're over here dropping slurs.
I know.
Um, yeah. So Manasa had to prevent of all that stuff. I mean, it's pretty, that's pretty bad.
He's in that's a pretty bad list of stuff. Yeah, it's awful. Like that's not like, oh, he, he lied.
Did these stole some stuff like burning your
children is pagan sacrifices.
Building.
Yeah.
Building altars to pagan gods and gods temple
and then going and dealing with necromancers
and videos.
That's kind of top tier sin in right there.
That's a.
Definitely top tier.
Yep.
So another example.
The people may not know as well or they may.
For certain reasons is in first macabees at a certain point after one of the battles of the macabee and revolt
Yeah, they start checking all the bodies
Yeah, they're side right
They're not like looting
Other side are checking their guys
And they find that a bunch of their guys are wearing like pagan amulets
Yeah, protect which which apparently did work so well
Clearly since they're dead
By the way, kids, you don't need to wear blue beads or the mud.
Or anything like that turns out that's not Christian.
Yeah.
But now you're canceled.
Greece is just canceled.
And Turkey and yes, great.
The war especially are upset at you after this.
And much of the Middle East.
And yes, anyway, it's a whole Mediterranean.
The world is kind of into the blue beads.
But so when they find these they go and they offer sacrifices for those dead soldiers
Right due to the sin they had committed right me there
They're death
So then as promised right as we mentioned
Once we get into the New Testament
when
People saw Christ doing miracles
They didn't accuse him of faking it.
Right, they didn't like debunk whether the miracle happened.
Yeah, I mean, people in the ancient world accepted that this kind of stuff was normal and real.
Yeah, but at least could happen.
Yeah.
And that there were certain special people, special for various reasons who could do these kinds of things.
Now some of the things that Jesus did.
Went beyond what they thought people could do, right? Like you and you see that in the text of the Gospels
Oh, yeah, like when he feels the man born blind, right like no one's ever heard of that
Yeah, like some of them were like sort of pushing the limit right and raising the dad was one of those limits that like
Normally we're on you know
But
Well, they see these things, they don't say, oh, that never happened.
Right or tried to debunk it or try to come up with some kind of other explanation
They just accused Jesus of sorcery essentially right and
One of the forms that takes is for example in Mark chapter three verses 23 through 27 where they accused him of
using the power of BL's above
Yeah, not you're a fake but rather you're using demons your bail. Yeah, yeah, basically
And so...
Christ, of course, condemns that no insert or disurbs. First, he says that makes no sense.
Why would the Prince of demons cast out demons? Yeah. But then also points out that's where
he talks about the blasphemy of the Holy Spirit, right? Because they're calling the Holy
spirit, the spirit of God, a demon, which is blasphemy and not just that.
But so obviously we hold that Christ's miracles were legitimate miracles the apostles right obviously the prophets of the
miracles they worked in the Old Testament. These wonders through Moses all that we think are God working through those people right but
But what this shows is that...
There are miracles that are done by people through demons.
Yeah, it's not.
That is a thing.
Yeah, it's not only that, that is actually a thing.
It's that one should not take some kind of miracle or what you might think of as a supernatural event
and say, oh!
This means that the person who did this or who seems to be the instrument of this, that
we should follow them and everything they do is good and holy, right?
A lot of different, not just Christian groups have miracles going on in them, but there
are plenty of testimonies to non-Christian religions of our own era.
Miraculous things happening.
the idea that you could point to one of those and say, ah, we are correct.
You know, no, that's that's not not how you do it. And I mean, it's notable
that while people can have their faith
Inspired or you know encouraged or whatever by experiencing something miraculous in the Orthodox Church the church does not
Like put up a big billboard
To a miracle. I mean, I there is for instance not too far from where I live. There is a mirror streaming icon and
and they actually forbid taking photographs in it.
church. I mean they could probably make money off of that if they wanted to, right?
You know, and attract as many people as possible to get the, you know, to put a lot of money in the basket.
But they don't because that's not how the Orthodox faith works. So even real, even miracles that are from God
are not used as, you know, some kind of proof. Ah-ha. Because it comes from Christ, right? Right?
So they ask Christ.
to do a sign for that.
Yeah, no.
To believe what he's saying, he never does, right?
Right.
In fact, he says, Kerset, are you?
Ask Kerset.
Right.
Again, like, you know, it's interesting in St. Luke's Gospel, it's faith, you know, that
a miracle usually kind of follows faith.
And then in John's Gospel, it's the opposite order.
But the point is that neither one is, in neither cases it used as a kind of proof.
Look what I just...
did. Right. Therefore you must and it can't be because there are false sides and wonders.
Right. And not false in the sense of it didn't happen, but false is the sense of it's from false
gods, gods who are not really rulers. Yeah. At Exhibit A, we've talked about this even fairly
recently. I think on the show in second Thessalonians 2 versus 7 through 10. We're saying false talking
when the man of lawlessness. Right? He talks about him working.
falls, working these sides and miracles through the energies of Satan.
Yeah.
Right. Like, literally says the energies of Satan.
So I mean, this is something that's saying, Paul, that yes, this happens.
Right. And so the fact that someone does those things doesn't prove anything in and of it itself.
Right.
Now we're also not saying that you should be credulous.
Sure. Yeah. There are fakes out there.
There are. There are people faking things.
Yeah.
Right.
Right. Yeah.
We don't need to burn David Blaine at the stake.
Okay.
Like, he's not really doing that stuff.
But like, if you ever see in leap of faith,
with Steve Martin, that's based on a real,
a real faker.
Yeah, that's based on that on the hint.
Yeah.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
He followed Benny Hinner round.
I can show you the interview where he talks about it.
He won't be sure.
If Benny Hincru says.
Yeah, it's actually based on a couple of different
of these faith dealers.
But there's one guy in particular who use the earpieces
and
and that stuff.
Oh yeah.
I can't remember his name right now.
But yeah.
Yeah, so yeah, there's Tony.
And I think it's Todd White who goes around
with the legs straightening thing.
Like that old gimmick thing.
I love the dude.
Is he the one who punches people in the stomach
to heal their demon possessions?
I don't know.
I don't think so.
Yeah.
But yeah, so yeah, there's a lot of phony baloney nonsense,
right?
And it's okay to call it out as phony baloney nonsense.
It's not being a modernist, right?
But there also is the reality that there are demonic forces of the world.
And so we shouldn't be scientific materialists with things bracken it off, which we hope
the fact that it could be that or somebody could be faking something right
Yeah, so we shouldn't just be naive and
cringeless. But especially we should keep in mind that even if someone does something
like that, right, and there's not sort of an easy debunk, that doesn't mean that what
they did came from God or had anything to do with God. Yeah, yeah, exactly. And doesn't
justify whatever it is they're teaching or preaching or whatever.
So now the probably the most famous magician in the Bible.
Oh yes. Simon Magus.
Yep. Simon Magus himself. The guy for whom Simon is named.
Yes. So Simon Vegas, I think...
Many, if not most of our listeners, are probably at least vaguely familiar with the place where he appears in the book of Acts, which we're going to read here in a minute.
But there's actually a lot of contours to this. We actually know a lot more about this person from other sources outside the Bible.
And a lot of the things we know about him are sort of alluded to and pointed to by the
text and acts.
In fact, if you know
this other stuff about him, a lot of the things this text and acts says about him that might
seem a little weird, like, makes sense.
Right.
But so we'll start with, here's where he shows up in the book of Acts in Scripture.
Yes.
So this is Acts chapter 8, starting with verse 9.
But there was a man named Simon who had previously practiced magic in the city and amazes
the people of Samaria saying that he himself was somebody great.
They all paid attention to him from the least to the greatest, saying this man is the power of God that is called great.
And they paid attention to him because for a long time he'd amazed them with his magic.
But when they believed Philip, as he preached the good news about the kingdom of God and the name of Jesus Christ,
they were baptized, both men and women.
Even Simon himself believed, and after being baptized, he continued with Philip,
and seeing signs and great miracles performed, he was amazed.
Now when the apostles at Jerusalem heard that some...
Maria had received the Word of God, they sent to them Peter and John, who came down and prayed
for them that they might receive the Holy Spirit, for he had not yet fallen on any of them,
but they had only been baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus.
Then they laid their hands on them and they received the Holy Spirit.
Now, when Simon saw that the Spirit was given through the laying on of the Apostle's hands,
he offered the money, saying, give me this power also, so that anyone on whom I lay my hands
I receive the Holy Spirit.
A Peter said to him,
May your silver perish with you,
because you thought you could obtain the gift of God with money.
You have neither part nor lot in this matter,
for your heart is not right before God.
Repent there for of this wickedness of yours.
And pray to the Lord that if possible,
the intent of your heart may be forgiven you.
For I see that you are in the gall of bitterness
and in the bond of iniquity.
And Simon answered,
Pray for me to the Lord that nothing of what you've said may come upon me.
So that's what's in Acts 8.
Yeah. So that's, yeah, that's what's in Acts 8.
You can see how he basically approaches what Philip and Peter and John are doing as magic,
right? This is some technique that if I pay you, you can teach me.
Yeah. I can do that.
Like a fully spirit thing.
And then I'll have the whammy that you guys have. Just teach me how to do it.
And when it says, he's going around amazing them with his magic and the things he's doing
and the wonders and things he's doing, and they're calling him the divine power, the great
divine power, right?
He's not going and pulling quarters out from behind people's ears, right?
This is like cool card tricks, right?
He's doing signs and wonders, right?
Then he sees Philip and he's like wow this guy's way
better than me, I got to learn how he does this, right?
Like that's his whole approach to this, right,
is this issue of technique, right?
And he doesn't fool,
Zayb Peter who tells him to buzz off.
So who is this guy?
Well, we know from,
St. Justin Martyr, St. Justin the philosopher
who lived there in...
in Palestine, in Samaria, that he is a fellow who was known as Simon of Gitta, Gitta being
a village in Samaria, who, according to St. Justin, did this stuff, was like a major figure
in Samaria. Remember St. Justin is in the second century.
So, he's less than a hundred years after this.
This is still a person whose name was well known, right, in that area, for having done all
these miracles and wonders and stuff.
And he had started sort of a little cult following who were named after him called the Simonians,
right, like basically the party of Simon, right.
Yeah.
He had this group of followers who sort of continued after him.
We also know from different church fathers.
that he wrote at least three different works.
Mm-hmm.
Uh, entitled, one entitled The Great Declaration,
one entitled The Four Corners of the World,
and one entitled,
Sermons of the Refuture.
That's a great name.
And a couple of these are quoted by
Epifadius of Salamis and his Pinariot.
Uh, the bread box.
Yeah. That's, um,
in order to sort of refute.
the Simonians. He's referred to in the Apostolic Constitutions as the Lawless One,
so like the Antichrist language that's sort of Belyal stuff.
Yeah. And we actually know about his death from a whole bunch of sources that
disagree on the details but have the same general idea. And that general idea is,
He went to Rome.
after this episode in Acts. He encountered at least St. Peter again, possibly also St. Paul,
and they had another negative encounter which involved Simon being able to levitate and him
falling to his death and getting ming.
So the details of this vary, but there's like a dozen versions of this from the acts of Peter to
say Cyril of Jerusalem mentions it in his kind of chemical lectures, like it's just all over the place.
It's your brothers and early writings.
Yeah, which strongly suggests that he was a big deal.
Yes.
Yeah, I mean, I think followers were still around.
As I recall, like, see Justin says, like all the Samaritans follow this game.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And the fact that that death story, even though again, the details are different,
whether it was just St. Peter, he read it to or whether it was St. Peter and Paul,
you know, some of them haven't just levitating, some of them haven't flying around over the city,
right? So there's, there's detailed differences. But the curtle of truth is that he fell to his death in
Rome. Yeah. After some other kind of encounter with St. Peter, right? And the fact that that's constant
through all these
versions of the story means I would argue there's you know it's hard to argue
there's not a historical kernel there right that of how he died of course you
know if you rule out miracles and stuff you know he wasn't levitating so what
did he and his followers believe well we actually know because of those quotes
from
epiphanias of Salamis, his quotes from Simon's writings. So they had this core story. This is sort of their main core
story that they believed. And this is wild people. This is wild stuff. So there's some quasi-nostic elements of it. For example, they have sort of God who's the, you know,
out. True one.
apophatic kind of vaguely platonic God. And then he has this emanation, which is his first thought,
and his first thought is female. And so this female first thought goes to create the angels.
Right, we're gonna be like the next step down.
from this female first thought, but when she creates the angels, the angels rebel against her.
And the angels go and create the material world and imprison her in it.
And she's imprisoned in the material world in a cycle of reincarnation.
So she keeps being born, living and dying.
over and over and over again. And she was Helen of Troy, most famously. But in the
first century AD, she was Helen, a Phoenician prostitute.
Who Simon met? So where does Simon Megas fit into this? Well, Simon proclaimed that he
He was God, whose first thought she was.
who had been incarnate as Simon in the world to go and rescue her.
And so Simon's followers thought, well, by becoming his followers,
at doing what he asked us to do,
when he escapes from this material world with her, he'll take us with him.
Hmm.
Right.
So that's what they were teaching. So you can see why they would look at him as an antichrist figure.
Yeah. Right. You can see what's being referred to when they talk about him saying that he himself was somebody great. Right. And the people saying this man is the power of God that is called great. Right.
That's what that's alluding to.
Right, that's alluding to that story, right? So, uh, yes, Simon Vegas, crazy cult leader of the first century AD declared that he was God at his Phoenician prostitute girlfriend was the first thought that emanated forth from the divine mind in prehistory.
Well, who are now going to escape from the material world with her? I mean, all you need is the Hillbop comment and like to write it today.
Some Nike's I know
Everything old is new again so wacky
So yes, there's some more info on Simon Vegas
Yeah, and what was up with that guy?
So then to sort of finish out, you know are sort of
Magic in the New Testament
Another little later in the book of acts when
St. Paul is on his missionary journeys. There's a scene that unfolds in Ephesus and Acts 19.
Yeah. Yeah. This is...
This is kind of a weird moment too. Okay.
Acts 19... Well, that's what this shows about, I guess. Starting with verse 13, then some of the
itinerant Jewish exorcists. How do you get that job? Under took to invoke the name of the Lord Jesus
over those who had evil spirits saying,
I adore you.
you by the Jesus whom Paul proclaims. Seven sons of a Jewish high priest named
Sceva were doing this, but the evil spirit answered them, Jesus I know and Paul I recognize,
but who are you? And the man in whom was the evil spirit leaped on them, mastered all
of them and overpowered them so that they fled out of that house, naked and wounded. And
this became known to all the residents of Ephesus, both Jews and Greeks, and fear fell
a
them all, and the name of the Lord Jesus was extolled.
Also many of those who are now believers came, confessing and devolging their practices,
and a number of those who had practiced magic arts, brought their books together and burned
them in the sight of all, and they counted the value of them and found it came to 50,000
pieces of silver.
So the Word of the Lord continued to increase and prevail mightily.
Yeah, so wandering Jewish exorcists.
Right.
But notice what they're trying to do.
They're trying to use the name Jesus.
Right.
This demonological way.
By the Jesus whom Paul proposes.
Yeah.
Not just any.
I have this name.
That guy.
Yeah.
The control and cast out demons.
That's a-
not how it works. Right? So the seven sons of Skava get thrashed. And yeah, I just, I
just picture this scene of like the, the guys, you know, fleeing the house and then that
grad theft auto wasted, like comes up on them. I have never played that game. So, but so
they get they get take it out right
But then this gets around.
Right.
This gets around.
And notice the response.
The response is all of these people giving up their magical practices.
Yeah.
Right.
Because what do they see?
They see that there's something superior about the way of life that St. Paul is preaching
to the kind of power and manipulation and that kind of thing that they've been seeking
through those practices.
And note how many like
How extensive this is, this is so many books and probably a lot of different people.
Yeah.
Apparently it's worth 50,000 pieces of silver.
I don't know exactly how much that would be in 20, 24 dollars, but probably a lot.
Yes.
That's like 2,500 gold pieces and standard Dungeons and Dragons conversion.
That's a lot of money.
Um...
So then one last bit when St. Paul is writing, as he does in Galatians 5, for example,
to former pagans now Christians and talking to them about the transformation of their
life and their way of life, right?
These magical practices are so common and so ingrained in the way of life of common people
that he has to sort of include them.
mention that is something that needs to be put off.
Yeah, yeah. So,
Inglations 5 versus 19 through 21,
he tells these ex-pagons. Now, the works the flesh are evident,
sexual immorality, impurity, sensuality, idolatry,
sorcery, enmity, strife, jealousy, fits of anger, rivalries,
dissensions, divisions, envy, drunkenness, orgees,
And things like these, I warn you.
as I warned you before, those who do such things will not inherit the kingdom of God.
It's quite the list. Yeah, but you notice things like sorcery have to have to be thrown in
there. Yeah, like don't do that. Right. And so again, if we're thinking of a certain way,
like really, there's a bunch of sorcerers, it's like, well, it's not that there were a bunch of
like professional sorcerers.
know, in the church is in Galatia, right? Galatia is a region. It's that there were lots of people
practicing these various things that were essentially sorcery, that were magical practices, right?
And those two had to be put off. Yeah. I mean, and again, not to belabor this point too much, but
But in our day, where we're so affected by philosophical material.
realism. We think of people who engage in this kind of stuff as weird out there fringe marginal
and they are, right, that they are in our world. But multiple times in the New Testament,
there's whole bunches of people that have to burn their books and be told not to do this
stuff and so forth. So it's simply much more prevalent because no one's a philosophical
materialist in the first century. It's just not not a thing.
You know people believe in magic they practice magic they wouldn't do it if they didn't
Believe that they were getting some kind of results and they were all indications that they were getting results
You know they're not dumb
Yeah, yeah, if they tried this stuff and it legit never worked they'd stop
right
Yeah, yeah, so all right
Well, we're gonna take our second break on this episode about the bread and cheese oracle
So
Other Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Planning your wedding and reception
can seem overwhelming with countless details
hijacking your time and energy.
in the book Crowned in Orthodox...
Christian Wedding Guide, author Christoph Adorchak and Delaney Claude Felter help you identify
your big three priorities to guide your decisions while keeping the emphasis on marriage as an
Orthodox Christian sacrament. Use this resource to help you simplify the process and keep
Christ at the center of your wedding day. Now available at store.inchantfaith.com. Again, that is
store.enginefaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey welcome back everybody.
Can you believe it?
Trudy cut me off right in the middle of...
I don't know what I'm gonna say.
You have the stage like it's the Oscars or something.
I know.
Hey, it's all love.
No love.
It's all good. It's all good. But we do have some collars actually. So we're going to go
ahead and talk with some people. So first we've got Bethany on the line. Bethany, welcome
to Lord of Spirits Podcast. What is up?
Hi. So first I want to say that this podcast is done in these things like volunteer
and I look at homeless shelter once a month, fight during fast seasons, make schools
prepares for that. But I go up to learn to people take up the tab.
But my question was to do with experiencing a supernatural reality.
So Father Andrew, you just mentioned a murdering icon down the street.
You previously mentioned many other examples of murdering icons,
as well as venerating the incorrect hand of sitting here in the end.
I have several friends who had mystical experiences and encountered murdering icons.
And I have friends who are even religious and have plenty to have meetings here at...
And I have another friend, Paul Cipobarker, who will admit to being a pure materialist.
And has told me he has seen ghosts.
And then when I reminded him of his materialist, he said it was really here because I believe
he can go.
Now, yes, many of these experiences come from different forces.
Clearly the more I've gotten started, God's spirit is probably not.
But I feel like I live in a pure, like a pure reality.
So why is it that some people have these miraculous...
experiences and others do not at all. Does it have to do with the news?
Yeah, I mean, it's a good question. I think there's multiple things that one
could say. So one of the things that I'll say is that God gives different
life, you know, experiences in life to different people for his purposes, right?
Each one of us has given everything that we need to repent and become a
So there's just variation in life, right?
But also, I will say, that I think people actually have spiritual experiences way more than they may realize.
You know, because our culture has taught us to discount, to dismiss this sort of thing,
So we're desensitized to it. We're much more likely to write it off to...
say, you know, it's a bit of mustard or undigested beef, right?
That kind of thing.
So I think all of those things are potentially in play.
Definitely some people have experiences that are much more palpable than others.
Most people's experiences that they describe out loud tend to be, you know, on the edge
of something. You know, like on the edge of perception or...
or that sort of thing. That's been my sort of anecdotal experience in that regard.
So not as much kind of just blatant in your face sort of stuff. But that stuff does happen.
It definitely does happen. I mean, it's not only like in testimony of the lives of saints,
so we see in scripture, but I mean, I've talked to people who have definitely had some of those kinds
of experiences. And as I mentioned, you know, some of the experiences that I've had are really like
when you watch.
Like one of the Merstreaming icons, actually two different
Merstreaming icons that I've encountered, not only did the
icon itself streamer, right?
Which like if someone was a super duper skeptic, they could
be like, well, the thing is meat of wood and it could be sort
of rigged blah, blah, blah.
Okay, sure, if you want to put that on there.
But the one that I don't get how you could possibly rig it is
in both cases of these icons, the case, the wooden case that
they were in, not only itself was sort of sweating
like the case.
was sweating it on the outside, but the glass on the front
is not just a drip down from the top,
which you could say, oh, well,
there's some kind of squirter in there,
but actually it formed in the middle of the glass
and then drip down.
I don't know how you make that happen,
like how you fake that.
I can't imagine, I don't know, maybe someone knows,
but I can't imagine how you do that,
but I watched it form so much that we had to continually
See you later.
it up. And I watched it get faster during a church service and then slow down at the
end. So I mean, this stuff to me is pretty unmistakable. I mean, it wasn't like spectacular
in the sense of like they were flashing lights or, you know, big music or whatever. It was
just like, oh, wow, it's a streaming mirror. How about that? You know, that's the experience.
And of course, I had this amazing fragrance. And yeah, there's a lot of a lot of testimonies
of people being healed as well. So I don't know if Father Stephen what he
about her question, why is it that some people seem to have these kinds of experiences and some seem
not to? Yeah, I mean ultimately it's like you said it's God gives different people different
experiences according to his knowledge. There's because I mean there are saints who have had
you know sort of the pinnacle of that experience that you can have in this life is to be
be hold to have the vision of Christ and His uncreated glory.
There have been saints who have had that experience once, relatively early in their life.
And they never again.
Yeah.
In their earthly life, never again.
And that's sort of its own cross of having had that and not being able to sort of get
it back, right?
Even though it's not something you can get, right? It's something God gives.
And there have been lots of saints.
I mean, people who are saints,
Pi is it devoted, who spent their whole life, you know,
in noetic prayer and never had that experience in this life.
We don't always know.
Part of it is we have to remember that God knows us better
than we know ourselves.
We have a way that we think we would react
to that kind of thing but
knows how we would actually react to that kind of thing. And I don't just mean fear. I mean,
that fear is an issue, right? Like a lot of people are not up for having a dead loved one,
like appear and talk to them, right? They would just assume not have that ever happen, right?
But beyond fear, like there's a danger of pride, there's a danger of developing
spiritual delusion
Right that can come from experiences
We all tell we all will say oh no, I would do that
Right, but God knows whether we do that
God knows whether we'd find likes with the dead loved one if we find it comforting or terrifying
He know right all these things right he knows and so we have to kind of trust his judgment
in terms of what he allows us
to experience and when in our earthly lives and that he knows sort of what's best in that
regard. But it sounds to me from the beginning of your question like you're doing the right
kinds of things, right? There's also a danger that sort of pursuing those kinds of experiences
we get so involved in that pursuit that we neglect the life in this world that God has called us to
while we're in this world. And it sounds like you're spending your time pursuing the things that
God has called you to in this world, which means you're doing the right things. And I think
that means while you're doing that, you could trust in God that he'll give you the experiences
You need to have and give them to you as gifts when and
how and in his timing, you know, in terms of when you need them.
Does that make sense, Bethany?
Yeah.
I like, I know I don't need this.
It's the only thing I was supposed to appear to be to have faith.
What do you say the same applies to the negative spiritual experiences?
Like the people who have spiritual experiences that aren't coming for God from God?
I should probably also mention people that they give intellectual, well,
I'll need that a little bit to honestly,
but I guess very far on the theater side.
I'm actually one of your Eastern Catholic friends.
What would the same applies like the negative experiences?
Yeah, I think God knows how you would react to a negative experience.
There's some people who would just be terrorized by it.
And there's some people who it might bring to repentance.
You know,
and so God knows which that is.
Because remember we've talked about the show how God kind of has the demons on a leash.
right and they just want to destroy us but he uses even their evil for our good.
Yep. Yep.
All righty. Thank you very much Bethany for calling.
All right now we've got Ron calling from Muncie, Indiana.
Ron welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Oh father and father.
a long time listener, first time caller.
All right.
So first off, thank you so much for taking my call.
You guys have helped me out a lot.
I am Jewish.
I was new age and at a hippie music festival.
I heard gospel.
And shortly after that, I had an axe chapter nine kind
of moment between me and God.
I got zapped with a new heart.
And...
I do a lot of work with kids.
My question for you is, I see new age just ramping up like mad.
I also was a Zen Buddhist for about 15 years.
I'm seeing an insurgents in mindfulness,
new age, tear card, crystals, just everything you were talking about.
My question would be how can the body of Christ
in general operate in more power and I don't want to say to attract people but just to use
what God has given to the body. I don't know if this is making sense. I was healed and delivered
firm drugs and demonic oppression and and I see that the my this is just my opinion and I'm asking
How do you...
think the gifts of the spirit can be in better use. I guess I'm saying to attract people
to understand who God is in a real way. And if I'm wrong about saying it that way, I'll
take the correction. That's my opinion and question to you. So what do you think?
Well, I think that the...
I'm trying to think of the best way to put this.
I guess I'll just be blunt so I don't have to think too long.
So I think that using what you're describing as the gifts of the spirit to attract people,
I don't think is the right way to go in the sense of, hey, look at what we've got.
We've got miracles and stuff.
I mean, I don't know what that's what you mean, but I'm definitely against that.
However, I mean, certainly like you.
When you see the gifts of the spirit described in the New Testament, right?
It's not only, I mean, I know a lot of people who have penicostal and charismatic background
and experience, they think of the gifts of the spirits in terms of things like speaking
in tongues and faith healing and all this kind of stuff that sort of seems to be supernatural
or whatever.
but actually, there's much more important things, like love.
Love is much higher than even raising the dead.
I think one of our saints even says that repenting of your sins is a greater miracle
than raising the dead.
So I would say that the key to outreach with regards to the gifts of the Spirit is repentance
on our own part, which is not just sort of this internal thing, repentance involves...
Like some of the stuff that our previous call was talking about, Bethany was saying,
I've been inspired to do this and this and this. And it was all stuff about sort of ministering
to the people around her. Right. And that's, that's what we see turns the empire upside down in the
first few centuries. As people are really noticed, like Julian, the apostate is mad that Christians
are willing to minister to non-Christians.
And he's like, why can't pagans be like this?
He wants pagans to have Christian ethics is his problem
You know and and many cases like there was plagues sweeping through the empire
It was the Christians who wouldn't took care of people even while everyone else was running off to the countryside to avoid the plague
You know so certainly I mean certainly if God gives to a person
a gift of
Wonderworking right
Although it's not like it's a possession of that person. It's God doing it
if God decides
to do that stuff through that person,
that's what's needed at that moment for that person.
But God's will for all of us in terms of our fellow humans
around us is pretty straightforward.
Love your neighbor as yourself.
Right, I agree to totally.
Like that's God's will for my life, for your life,
Father Stevens' life, everybody's life.
Can I quickly amend my question to,
Yes, I will.
I see.
new age just ramping up and it's not so much that I want advertised Jesus with
Miracle Signs and Wonders but I because I've been healed and emotionally
set free and I've got a new heart like you were talking about I just I I don't
know if I I do agree with you it's the love and ministering that makes it
shines a light. What do you think?
Is the proper place of the gifts in the body?
What do you think father?
Yeah
Well, so I think part of the part of the thing here is that
New age spirituality is pretty thin gruel
If you've got a generation of young people who are starving
because they are raised to the flat gray meaningless world with no spirituality whatsoever.
It's attractive because at least it's something, right?
But
Right now in America
Getting into the new age stuff is is this transitory phase into getting into all kinds of other things
There's a whole phenomenon of
Conspirituality now where a lot of the people getting involved in things like QAnon and stuff are coming out of the new age movement
Okay, right.
Which you wouldn't.
Yeah.
intuitive, right? But people are going through the
next two other places. The advantage we have when it comes to spirituality is that we have
the real deal. If new age spirituality is thin, cruel, then we're serving steak, right? And
And so, and that's on all levels.
That's on the level.
of explaining people's spiritual experiences that's in terms of meaning in the world, that's in terms of,
as Father Andrew said, the greatest miracle being the conversion and repentance of a person.
one of the things so very early
when I was coming into the Orthodox Church 20 odd years ago now. One thing that really
impressed me is I remember I went and I looked up on some website about a
murder-streaming icon like Father Andrew was talking about with the previous
caller, this miraculous icon that had murder-streaming from it. And there
were sort of these testimonials of people who had come to see it and come
they're in prayed.
And what impressed me was half the testimonials.
Didn't have anything to do with healing
or anything like that.
Half the testimonials were talking about, you know,
for example, this was in one of the major,
especially violent urban areas of the US.
A grandmother bringing her grandson there
who was in a gang.
And he repented and left the gang
and started coming to church with her.
And...
you know, we can follow him Christ.
Like that's listed there is,
look at this miracle that happened.
Right.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, no, I'm gonna die.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay, yeah, yeah.
And that's super impressed me.
You know, when I was,
when I was first coming into the church
because I was like, that's it, right?
And like, that's the whole thing there.
And so I think,
A big part that we neglect when we think about the role of all of the gifts that St. Paul talks about
The greatest of which is Father Andrew said his love
Is that part of that gifting is the gifting that comes to the people who are coming in
Right
Part of that gifting
When someone comes into the community when they come into the church, right?
where they receive
the Holy Spirit, they receive gifts. Oh yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, got you. Right.
Got you. And I don't think those of us who are older have fully realized the sense of
meaninglessness and purposelessness that a lot of young people. Yeah. Okay. What it's
like to just feel like you're not good at anything. There's nothing
special about you, you have nothing to contribute.
You know, you have no purpose, right?
And coming into a community where now you have something to contribute,
unique to you, and you have a place and a purpose and a role in that community.
I think that is incredibly powerful now in our present cultural moment.
and that's something that like
new age spirituality can't give you. Right.
Remotely. Yep.
All right. Well, I hope that's helpful to you, Ron. Thank you very much for calling.
Oh, that was great. Seriously. Thanks so much for, you know, I've been, I've been
watched all your stuff. So and I'm going to steal it. And then I'll give you a
footnote somewhere. You guys really have been champs and like, and then now I get to go talk
about Johnny's Thomas.
friends will go, they know everything.
People get excited when you talk about,
I know, I know, no, no.
Thanks again, back.
And if I just sound too informal, I'm sorry,
but Bella's thinks a bunch, I do appreciate it.
God bless you Ron, thanks.
All right.
Well, where's the cheese, Father Steve?
My only problem with Bella's is that he assumed my gender.
But what?
If you're a lady, I don't know what reality,
I'm in, so I don't know what to tell you.
I'm definitely not a lady.
I could tell you that.
So, all right.
It's the third half and we promised people the cheese sandwich
Oracle and we'll get to,
we're not jumping straight there.
In a few minutes, yes.
Yes, we're not jumping straight, no, no, no, no.
It's funny, on the YouTube's people are like,
when's the cheese?
Have they gone to the cheese yet?
Did I miss the cheese?
She's sandwich, not just cheese people.
The cheese sands a lot.
And not grilled cheese.
No one said it was grilled cheese.
We don't know that it was grilled cheese.
I'd like to think it was grilled cheese.
I mean, that would be nice.
I do love a good grilled cheese.
But, yeah.
Okay.
So, what's left?
What's left now?
So this is our third half.
We're now we will explain to you
the scientific basis of the whammy.
So, what we're gonna talk about now is,
So we've talked now.
about magic in the ancient world a little bit. We've talked a little bit about how that
butts up against the scriptures and the old and new testaments. Now we're going to talk
about post scriptures, what happens to all of this, to all of this magic, right, to these
practices. And as well as they don't just vanish and go away.
Now the primary place where they're going to survive
pretty much everywhere is going to be on the level of folk magic.
Yeah, like so.
Now this is a blanket thing.
This again is the shack out in the bayou kind of thing.
Yeah, not that I'm trying to think.
Well, or just since just rural people.
A swamp.
Yeah, right, right exactly.
Yeah.
And the reason for this is that Christianity has been fairly
successful at driving these practices.
out of the community.
In urban places, yeah.
It's no longer front and center,
the way that it used to be.
But so things that were sort of magical practices
integrated somewhat with pagan religion
just sort of become folk traditions.
Yeah.
Even though they're separated from the religion
that sort of bore them.
Right.
The sort of formal religious practices that bore them.
but they kinda st-
and they linger around all, I mean, and there's variations on this, but there's versions of this everywhere up until this present day.
Yeah, yep. Right. You've got German folk magic. You've got, right. I mean, all all over the place.
But so that's sort of on an informal level. That's sort of a constant. Just about anywhere you go. Right.
any time in history. But now we're going to talk about some more
particular and official sort of interactions and forms that these magical
practice and traditions have taken over the course of the last couple of
millennia. So we have to start out with the fact that from a Roman perspective,
from the earliest Roman perspective on Christianity, so we're talking the end
of the 1st century AD.
The Romans believed that the Christians were practicing magic.
Yeah.
That's what they said about them.
So they believed that they do wish magic.
Yeah, they were doing real stuff, but not their pagan real stuff.
Right.
So, and exhibit A of this is at the end of the
very end of the first century during Demetians' persecutions. Right? This is the, these are the,
this is the first major Roman imperial persecution of Christians. This is when St. John,
the evangelist ends up on Patmas. Right. During that Demetians' persecution,
We have trial records.
of some prominent Roman Christians, very prominent, wealthy,
patrician Roman Christians, when Achilles glabrio and Tishius Flavius Clemens,
I mean those are some awesome Roman names right there.
It is hard to get more Roman names than those.
Yes. Those two were executed by beheading.
And Clemens Wife, Flavia Domitila, who was the Emperor of Espossians' granddaughter.
So an important noble person.
So descended from the Imperial family, these are important noble people.
Because of her being the granddaughter of a former emperor, she was just exiled, instead
of being executed.
And the two men were executed and she was exiled for participating in Jewish
rituals and magic, which was the formal way that Christians were charged, whether Roman
and period of government.
And this is not just sort of the Romans trying to figure out where in Roman law, they
could come up with an excuse for executing Christians, right?
Say it's witchcraft, right?
This was their view.
So when you get to in the middle of the...
century, Kelsus, who famously origin responded to in Contra Kelsus. Kelsus says that when he's giving his
counter-narrative to attack Christianity, and Kelsus is attacking Christianity, the second century was
considered the greatest pagan sort of polemic against Christianity. That's why origin responded to it
other
people responded to it. Kelsa says that when Jesus fled to Egypt he learned magic
there. Yeah, as a toddler. He learned sorcery. And so that's how he came back and did all of
these wonders is that he had learned Egyptian sorcery. Porphyry, so we're moving ahead, not quite
another century.
Porphyry, who along with Plotinus, is kind of the founder of Neoplatanism, virilently anti-Christian.
People forget Neoplatanism was a deliberately anti-Christian philosophical movement.
It was an attempt to sort of vaguely Christianize and religiosity, I guess.
Plotonic philosophy to compete with Christianity in the third century, as Christianity was spreading
in the Roman Empire.
but Porphyry are used that not just Jesus,
but the apostles were all sorcerers,
who he taught magic to.
And that's why the apostles could work miracles.
Yeah, because I mean, if you're a pagan,
right, I mean, you see this religious group,
they're doing miracles or whatever,
that's the easy frame to put on it.
Right.
And then for him, it has no religious significance.
Yeah, they just learned these techniques and went and did sorcery. That doesn't mean you should listen to what they say. Right. Right.
That's why they considered it a counter-argument.
You also have within Gnostic sects, sects. They absorb a lot of pagan magical practices.
Even as Christianity.
is reputing them, these nostics have sort of absorbed them in terms of some of their tax
onamies absorbing, you know, they have the the agdo ad and all that.
You know, all these taxonomies of spiritual emanations and and divine emanations, a lot of that
is taken over from pagan demonologies.
They take over a lot of names.
They get named and named over people in initiation rituals and things.
I mean, and it makes sense too, right? Because nosticism is
so focused on kind of like achievement, right?
So give them some techniques to do
where they can retie and become truly spiritual
and sluff off this mortal coil.
Yeah, yeah.
And then when we get to the fourth century,
when we get to the fourth century,
we've got one more century to go
and then we're at the cheese sandwich.
It's happening people.
Gather around your radio.
The Irracular Cheese Sandwich.
I'm pretending someone is listening to this show on one of those big upright radios
from the 1940s, like with the lounge chairs.
Then there's a photo of you and your family doing it everybody.
Yeah.
So in the fourth century, we have sort of three sources that tell us interesting things about
magic is doing the 4th century.
So this is, we're now into the era of constancy.
Yeah.
So one of those sources is Amy Anis Marcellinus,
who writes a history and talks about
sort of the post-constantinian bands
on different magical practices.
Or then of course we have the Codex Theodosianis,
right, Theodosian's code.
which has laws banning things like astrology, divination, amulets, and the possession of
quote unquote secret books.
It's interesting.
I mean, pagan rulers don't do this kind of thing.
They don't ban all that stuff.
Yeah.
And then the third source is kind of interesting because it's, so, Lybanius of Antioch
is an important figure in the fourth century.
He was the teacher of St. John Chrysostom in rhetoric.
Right, right.
But remained a pagan his whole life.
Yeah.
But part of the reason why things have survived from him is the high respect that St. John
and others held him in despite him being a pagan.
And he was, so he's the most important figure of that last generation of pagans in the mid
fourth century and was incredibly learned.
at the time, obviously, and wrote an autobiography about his life.
And in terms of what we're talking about tonight, what's relevant there is that even though he's
this sort of super philosophical advanced pagan would never do something so, you know,
petty and rustic as sacrifice an animal, right?
Like completely believes that magic works completely believes that all that stuff
works. Yeah. Yeah. Right. And expresses worry, expresses worry that with the Christian
bands on these things, right, that he yet others might be in danger. If they can't have
their amulets and two definition and things. Right. That they're going to be in trouble.
Because I remember again, like this was seen by pagans on kind of on the level of like,
I'm not saying it-
placed medicine they had doctors too, but that's that's the level of integration it was into people's lives
So he was like concerned like wait a minute. They're taking away this important part of life. Yeah
Well, it's sort of like people people today
Right well, I was gonna say today that I was gonna mention a newspaper but
What's a newspaper on exactly but people will get a look at the weather
Forecast right for the next few days and they'll look at you know
So...
if they're not broke like me, they'll look at like how the
markets are trending.
Right, they'll try to get all of this information so they
can plan things.
Right, over the next few days, right?
And that's sort of how they viewed things like
Abueless and Dividation, right?
You gotta keep track of what's going on, right?
I mean, yeah.
Exactly.
You gotta be prepared for what's coming, you know.
Yeah, so.
Um,
I see it expresses some difficulty.
So now finally, friends, the moment has arrived.
We come to the man himself,
Sofronius of Tella,
at the story of the cheese sandwich Oracle.
Again, this morning I did not believe that this was real
and now I know that it is.
The ordeal of bread and cheese is about to begin.
So that's what it says in the source is the word
deal of bread and cheese.
Yes.
So, Sofronius was the Bishop of Tella.
He wasn't from Tella, he was the Bishop of Tella.
Which I think is like in South, roughly kind of
South Eastern Turkey now.
Yeah.
He was a, the story.
Not in the sense of his beliefs.
We don't have that good of a window in his beliefs.
Apparently he believed in some wacky stuff
we're about to find out.
But, but he was like literally friends with the story is.
Right.
Like friends with the guy himself and it kind of stuck up for him.
Yeah.
Not enough to get exiled with him, but it kind of stuck up for him.
He shows up at the robber council of 445, right?
449.
Yeah.
And then also shows up at Calcedon, a couple years later.
But it's the robber council where this, the cheese and bread.
Yeah.
So when he shows up at the Robert Council, so he goes to both the Robert Council and the
Ecumenical Council.
So as you can see, what exactly he believed?
Right.
But when he showed up at the Robert Council, someone brought charges against him.
Clergy from his own diocese.
Yes.
David brought charges.
Yeah, it seems that some money had been stolen from him, and so he was trying to...
He had three possible suspects.
So he was trying to figure out who's the guilty part.
you do one of them
did it. Yes, but not which one. So first he did something that seems like something maybe
a bishop might do. He had each of them come and swear an oath on the gospel book that
they did not do it because he figured, hey, whoever did it, they're not going to come and
swear an oath before God on the gospel book. Right. So this will get them to admit it.
But all three of them saw the oath. None of them admitted it. And so then he said, we
with
use the cheese sandwich oracle. So he erected a small stand. The kid were not, I swear, we're
not making this up. Look up. So phronious of tele, T-E-L-L-A, and you will discover the
cheese sandwich oracle story. He erected a small stand. Now imagine your bishop did this and you
you're going and telling the council about it anyway
you said I was a Kivas trade face
He sets up a small stand and he lays out on the stand three cheese sandwiches.
Bread and cheese.
Prepared in a certain manner. And invited the three to come and eat the sandwiches
in the belief that because of how he had prepared the sandwiches, the guilty party would not be able to
eat and would vomit up.
sandwich. But in fact, we are told not only did all three eat the sandwiches, they ate them quite
ravenously. So apparently it was not much of an ordeal. The bread of the cheese. So then he moved to
the nuclear option. Yeah, right. Yeah, the funny thing is the bread and cheese oracle is not actually
sort of the climax of the story. So I'm going to
read now to you a passage that is from the early 20th century Catholic and
psychopedia which sort of summarizes what happens. So this not succeeding, that
is to say the cheese sandwich oracle, this not succeeding, he had recourse to the
divining cup. He used the sun of one of his servants as a medium and with two
others, again this is a bishop you guys, and with two others after some
incantations.
place the youth before a vessel containing oil and water. In this mixture, the youth first saw flames of fire.
Then, quote, a man sitting on a throne of gold and clad in purple and a crown upon his head.
End quote. After this, they put the oil and water in a hole near the door and the medium saw the bishop's son, Habib,
who was returning home from Constantinople. Seated on a black mary mule that is blindfolded and behind him two men on foot.
The lad confessed these and other like things on oath.
He was haunted by seven men dressed in white and lost his reason and was with difficulty
cured by being brought into holy places and anointed with oil.
What is going on in Tella?
But apparently this vision revealed who the guilty party was.
Yes, apparently.
Apparently.
And it caused the poor kid who he used as a medium to lose his mind.
to coat, yeah, he had to be taking the holy places and
anointed with oil.
with difficulty cured.
The seven men dressed in white were hunting him.
They were not anti-nazgo.
So there you are everybody.
That is the cheese sandwich oracle
and then the weird, divining cup, oil and water.
That's a pretty advanced pagan magical practice.
Yeah.
That's still around being done by this...
So a shifty bishop.
Yeah, or at least, I mean, like...
Of the fifth century.
from what I read it was
never like clear whether he was like convicted of this stuff but this is what his clergy
said about him you know weirdly specific.
Make a bunch of denunciations and stuff at the Council of Calcedon.
Yeah yeah you better profess Calcedon or take a beaten Sephornius of Tella.
So yeah, anyway.
So even in circles like this, this kind of stuff was...
still around in the fifth century.
And we know that there were still problems with it
even later, one example, John Mammaconian,
who is a saint in the Armenian church,
wrote what's called the letter on devilish sorceries
and the godless conjurations.
Yeah, which is interesting because this is,
yeah, seventh century Armenia.
I mean, it's a very Christian country by that point.
I mean, in fact it's the first...
officially Christian country, Armenia, right?
So that's kind of stuff is still around.
And so as a result, you need,
churchmen are writing things against it.
You don't see rules made against things
that no one's doing.
And somebody grabbed the album title,
devilish sorceries and the godless conjurations.
Pretty solid.
That could also be the name of a tour.
A vintage tour.
Yeah, yep.
Right, so...
Now moving, you know, moving through history a little more, there is what comes to be called
the esoteric tradition, which involves a whole bunch of different things. But a lot of
it is the continuation of these sort of magical traditions and practices. You find this in
Hermeticism, which is of course named
after Hermes, trimigistus, the right splice in Hermes,
who's not as anxious as they thought he was, but...
Yeah, right.
But that Hermetic tradition in the medieval period
takes them pretty firm root in various places.
That sort of flowers through the Renaissance
and enlightenment and you end up
with the early stages of free masonry.
I am not a person.
Controversial. I'm not a person who gets super hot and bothered about free mates and recurrently. I'm not afraid of old men in small cars.
I'm haunted by seven old men in small cars wearing white clothes.
And you know, I've never met a Mason under 50, which means we won't have to worry about them for much longer.
Yeah, they're kind of going away.
Yeah, but especially the early phases they're definitely a repository for a lot of these traditional traditions, right?
Yeah, and I think those early phases especially they took a lot more of the ritual stuff they do
Let's say a lot more seriously that the average Shriner in 2024 does
Yeah, they're also probably sober most of the time
But then you really see this
when you get into the late night
the early 20th century in spiritualism,
Madalmovatsky, right?
All of the new thought religious groups,
and the groups that spin out of it,
like Christian science.
Christian science is the grape nuts of religion
because grape nuts has no grapes.
Maybe the grapes are nuts, yeah.
Christian science is neither Christian nor scientific.
Yeah, it's interesting, like the 90s.
century there's this whole new thought movement which kind of has at its
base the idea that either that the material world is not real or that it's
really subject to something called mind you know or some of both right yeah
it's sprouted some some really curious curious stuff yeah but you get again
medium.
You get a lot of this, these phenomena, right, of magic, mediums, contacting, spirits,
demonology, all of these things, popping up again, and having sort of a cultural moment
at the time.
Yeah, I mean, a number of elites were really into this kind of stuff.
Yeah.
and a brave guy like Houdini going around
and debunking them and messing with them.
Um...
Fun.
And then we have to mention Carl Jung,
who very much makes a study of all of this tradition.
So he has multiple books he wrote on the Hermetic tradition.
He has a two volume work on alchemy.
Right, so he deeply immerses himself in this stuff
Before we found the knife...
the dog homody library, all of the
surviving Gnostic texts that we had were
collected in what was called the Jung
Codex because he collected them.
Right, so he was very interested in this
whole tradition, studying it.
For the most part he took it in a
psychological direction, like he did
and everything else.
Was he just a weird psychologist?
It sort of structures of consciousness
that kind of thing.
But other...
other hand he had a weird personal life which included him starting a cult in his house
and during their quote-unquote meetings he would walk around naked wearing a lion head
and referring to himself as the Aryan Christ.
Yeah that's pretty normal for a psychologist.
Yeah right.
When I say a lion head I don't mean like he had a furry lion head made.
I mean, like a taxidermy lion head.
Just so you get.
full portrait here. Oh wow. Interesting cat. Pun intended it. And then as we were talking
about with the most recent caller, a lot of this then trickles out into various new age
stuff. Although by that point, it's awfully watered down. Although yeah, and it's super
Yeah, and you do get full blown.
People doing full-blown medium stuff full-blown, right? So there is some sort of full-blown versions of this within that
but a lot of it is very thinned out
and
Deliberately so for a couple of reasons number one so it you know capitalism so it could be
So you know buy your crystals and
Right, so it could be bought and sold and marketed and also because
that kind of spirituality was aimed at an
America.
going through the 60s that was averse to religions
that demanded things of you.
Yeah, this is all about religions
that gonna do something for you.
Yeah, it's always very choose your own adventure, right?
Yeah.
Although I have to say, I think my favorite encounter
with someone who is, you know, not just like a shopper
at a new age bookstore, but you know, I think it was,
I don't know, might've been a proprietor.
I was walking.
his street and someone at one of these places, I mean, I wasn't going into this place.
I don't go into such places.
But someone came out and invited me and the people that were with us.
They said, Hey, you want to come in?
We're going to be channeling the Archangel Michael later.
I was like, I hope for your sake that he doesn't show up.
So he might show up and say that to it is.
I don't know.
go well with you my friend. Yeah. Either way. Yeah, it's funny. It's funny because yeah,
like why would you even say that if you actually had a clear biblical view of the archangel
Michael, you know, leader of the heavenly host, the guy who tosses the dragon out of heaven,
like the Reaper of Souls. Like really? You're going to invite him to your house, you know?
Now, now, you know.
summon the Archangel Michael.
Anyway.
Yeah. So, now it's my turn to get people mad at me.
At least at the past people have gotten mad at me.
I found that there's a segment of the audience at least that doesn't like it when I take somebody who goes around calling themselves a Christian
and I point out that they're not one.
But I'm about to do that again.
in. Kenneth Copeland, not a Christian, and our biblical terms should probably be stoned
to death. I mean, I mean, I mean, we stoned him to death. Right. No, no, by no means, you
know, going by the Torah. Right. I was disrespectful to my father. So you'd have to stoned me
first. Yes, exactly. Right. We've all done. We've all done here. But yeah, calling for violence
to your people.
It says, I mean, it says in the scripture, again,
like you made this point earlier,
like if someone's prophecy doesn't turn out,
once even, that means they're not a real prophet.
And yeah, the Torah talks about what to do with a fault.
In St. Gregory it's not so hot.
Right.
But you're Kenneth Copeland, you're Benny Hinn,
they're ilk, you're Bethel folks.
Bethel School of Supernatural Ministry.
You're prosperity gospel people, you're word faith people.
Yes.
All of these folks together, okay?
Not Christians. That's not Christianity.
It just isn't. It's a different religion.
That they're preaching. Many hint in particular has no excuse. He's in apostate.
We don't need to go into that anymore. But,
because what they're preaching is magic.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, it's, it's, they're claiming magical powers.
Yeah, and what's interesting is like,
especially some of the early word faith people,
we're actually reading and mingling with some of the new
thought types and their texts that come out of the late 19th
century.
So there's action.
this direct connection with some of this theosophist spiritualist stuff of that period.
And what they have in common is this idea that you can use language and thought to manipulate reality.
Right? And the way that word faith guy is packages is they'll say, well, words are like containers.
You know, and faith is this substance that, you know, they use that language from the Bible,
the way to the face, the substance of things, hope for whatever. But like faith is
a substance, like it's a thing that makes things happen in the world. And so that's why like if you
just decree and declare and really believe and everybody believe with me, then then things will
happen that you want to happen, whether it's wealth or or miraculous healing or whatever it might be.
You know, and you get like the water down affirmations of people like Joel Osteen and that kind of
stuff. And it's all about like using language and thoughts.
to create physical effects.
And that's what magic is people.
I'm sorry, that's what magic is.
Someone who preaches Christianity,
preaches repentance and faithfulness to Jesus Christ,
and that's not what they're preaching.
Right.
They're preaching that you are equal to Jesus.
You are just like Jesus.
You have all the powers Jesus had.
Yeah, I mean, some of them even say,
well, Jesus, you know, if you embrace them.
Right that that that he he
He was able to do this because he's man, and so you can too.
Yeah.
There's no repentance involved.
Nothing about repentance.
Yeah.
Nothing about sin.
God doesn't want you to suffer.
It's over.
This isn't Christian.
Despite all that stuff, and from the Lord about in this world, you will have trouble.
And if we want to say the pseudo meaning false brethren, right, the false Christians were
talking about.
or not Christians.
Right? If they're sort of, if we want to use these terms from the French Revolution
that we use for everything now, if they represent the right end of this, right? Because they're
making a pretense to evangelical Christianity, evangelical Protestantism. Then the left
side of this is Oprah Winfrey.
Right.
And the secret.
Yeah, right look look that up everybody and there's also like there's this thing called a
Corson miracles right
Which will and blame she channeled Jesus right and wrote it while in a trance. Yeah. Yeah, I
If you're interested in some of you know at least understandings from this kind of stuff
Um, I do happen to have written it into one of my some of it into one of my books. It's an orthodoxy and heterodoxy
So some of that is covered there like if you're just in the collection
between worth faith and new thought,
but also some of these other odd things
that you get over the last hundred or 200 years.
It's in there as well.
But yeah, it's, I don't know, it's a wacky temptation.
Not wacky in the sense of rare, sadly,
but really weird that Christians,
people call themselves Christians,
would go after this stuff.
You know?
Yeah, yeah, but yeah, and it's it's
The allure is oh you can have everything you want the very dark side of it whether we're talking about a Kenneth Copeland or an Oprah Winfrey is that
If your life then isn't wonderful and perfect. It's all your fault
Yeah, because you don't have enough faith and you spoke negativity into the world and blah blah blah blah, right?
was that Kenneth Hagen?
said that he never was sick at past a certain point or whatever.
Yeah, there's a lot of that. Yeah. Yeah.
It's at its hideous, right? When you see it from that side.
Right. But the most hideous thing about it, right?
And I mean, I think even Oprah Winfrey and some of these secret people,
like Course in Miracles, supposedly was channeled from Jesus, right?
Even they are putting this veneer of like liberal Protestant Christianity on it.
Yeah, the most hideous and
thing about this is that it's being put forward as if it were Christianity. Right? And so not only is
the name of Lord Jesus Christ being drugged through the mud by these people, by these false prophets and
false teachers. But but people are being given promises and told these horrible things that then
when they're burned out and they realize, you know, the horror of this.
They want nothing to do with Christianity,
because this is what they think Christianity is.
Yeah.
That's why I'm being so clear that this is not Christianity.
Yep.
Right. And I'm at the point with this stuff,
frankly, where like,
if you're going to call somebody like Kenneth Copeland
or Benny Hinn your brother in Christ,
right, if you're not willing to say that they're not a Christian,
then you know I have to follow
what the New Testament says, and I can't have any fellowship with you either.
Yep. Right. Like, we have to be clear about this. The apostles told us we have to be clear about
this. Identifying false teachers. Okay. This isn't, and you listeners, you know, I don't talk this
way about like regular Protestants. I don't talk this way about the Pope or regular Roman Catholics.
Okay.
I reserve this kind of stuff for the really heinous.
All right.
This is, these are the people who say John is talking about it first John.
These are the people who say Paul is talking about over and over again.
These are the wolves that Christ said would come.
And we have to be completely, completely clear about that.
Yeah.
All right.
Okay.
wrap up our episode on magic.
I think that this is very relevant.
It's not, again, this is not just,
oh look here's some weird esoteric stuff.
I mean, she's sandwiched oracles and all.
As fun as it is to kind of look at stories like that.
I think that especially for...
people living in the culture that that Father Steven and I live in, you know, 21st century
America.
And maybe this applies to some people because I know we have people over the world listening
to us.
So hello, everybody else.
We're so glad you're here.
If this applies to your culture too, then I hope that this is helpful.
If not, you can just pray for Americans, if you don't mind.
I think that this temptation to magic is
actually endemic because what is magic about? It's about doing the thing that you need
to do in order to get the thing that you want. And especially with a sense that you can
control your world. Right? And the fact that we have this technological mastery of our world
that we think we have, although I mean, I think about the poor people right now, I mean,
a lot of suffering all over the world.
I think about, for instance, about the poor people in Texas, who a lot of them just lost
power because of hurricane.
And there's also incredible heat going on right now.
That's very dangerous, that combination, because there's not air conditioning to keep people
safe.
It's not just about comfort, safe and extreme heat.
We don't really have mastery of the world.
can still definitely be inter-
erupted and overcome even. But I think the temptation of magic is about this
sense of mastery, right? And think about Simon Mages. What is it he's trying to do?
He's trying to control. He wants the power. So he's willing to pay for it.
probably with a thought to hey I can get paid to you know uh this is real pride
This is the attitude that this life is about me.
What I want.
I mean, honestly, this is also what's behind cancel culture.
What is cancel culture at its base?
It's, I should not ever have to be exposed to anything that I disagree with.
Right?
Because I need the ultimate control.
I should be able to click a button and everything be just fine.
That is the temptation to man.
That is a temptation of magic.
It's no surprise to me that as Christian culture collapses, as the meta-narrative of Western
culture collapses, that there should now be an increase not just of magic in the metaphorical
sense or even just the technological sense, but in the actual literal sense.
people doing.
rituals to try to make things happen. But whether using a ritual or not, this sort of illusion
of control, this desire for control, it's about pride, it's about lust, it's really,
it's that, that is the sin. And, you know, we talked at the end about prosperity, preachers,
word faith and
and kind of opus spirituality and this stuff.
And as we were talking about that,
I thought about the example of the saints
because here are people that
not only did not look for control, right?
It wasn't about being tough and about being,
and command the world and what.
the opposite, right? The opposite. It was about repentance, about repentance and
what is repentance? Repentance is to be faithful to Christ, to live according to
the way that he commanded, right? That's what repentance is. And if like in our
culture wheat.
you know, you should try to change the world.
Like everyone can grow up and change the world.
Number one, most of us are not that important.
We're not.
Like you can't go in and change the world.
I'm sorry.
It's just not true.
Like that's, most people in history will be forgotten.
That is the reality, right?
Most people are forgotten by the world.
They don't change the world.
get forgotten by the law.
And it's not because they didn't try hard enough.
But if you really actually want to change the world like if you want to want to actually make the world better
If you want to bring it closer into the justice and the beauty and the order of God then
the the place you start is to repent a
Holy person affects everyone around them, but they didn't get holy by
By doing some formula
They got holy by living humbly.
They got holy by repenting of their sins.
They got holy by serving other people by putting themselves last.
Right? And you know, it's funny.
Like there's even this temptation of magic that exists.
I mean, this might sound a little esoteric to some people.
And if you're never hurting this, God bless you.
I envy you.
But there's even temptation of magic that exists
amongst some Orthodox like on the internet,
where they'll try to pick apart
sacraments, for instance, and unless there's a specific formula or whatever it might be to say
nothing about the church's tradition and history about these things, but like no, no, no, it's this one
model that could and must do this way or else you're not Orthodox or you're not whatever
you know, and people especially apply this to baptism, frankly, and especially the way that people
received into the church.
And that just is a profoundly ignorant view when you look at the actual whole history
of the way the churches dealt with these things because the church is not a magic factory.
The church is a place for people to repent.
The church is a place for people to become like Christ.
And it gets people to that point in a lot of different ways even though ultimately the
path of repentance is the same.
If you focus on these formulas, I'm not saying...
I'm not saying that the way that services are done does not matter. The way the sacraments are done does not matter.
It matters, right? It needs to be done in obedience to the church according to the tradition of the church.
All that kind of stuff. I am by no means like a reformer or an innovator or any of that stuff.
I'm not interested in that. I didn't become Orthodox for that.
But if you become fixated on a kind of mechanistic understanding, a magical understanding of life in the church,
And it doesn't just have to be sacraments of other people who have this idea of
like, oh, you have to do your piety in this particular way.
And church services must be done only in this particular way.
And whatever it might be, like all this kind of focus
on particular details like this,
as though that it's the details themselves
that make it happen, that's magical thinking,
that's magical thinking.
And it's all about distraction from real repentance.
And you can tell that because the spirit that goes along
with that.
magical thinking is usually very harsh, very hard, and does not inspire anyone to actually
meet Christ and to repent and to become like him, to love their fellow humans, to put others
in front of them, to sacrifice themselves. It doesn't. It doesn't. I've been around
long enough to say that I've never seen it work that way.
What is the opposite of magic? Repentance. Repentance is the opposite of magic.
Repentance is to let go of control. Repentance is to surround yourself to
Christ and to do His will and not seek to exert your will over other people.
All right, rant over.
You're stealing my bit. Oh, I didn't know that you were going to rant in that
particular way but no.
Oh no, just ran to general.
Oh, okay.
No.
So on three separate occasions,
I have won the publishers clearing out sweepstakes.
Did someone show up at your door?
Or did you just get it in the mail?
No, you've seen one of the checks.
I sent you a picture.
Oh.
Twice, I won five dollars.
Hey.
The third time I won the princely sum.
of ten American dollars.
Woo wee!
Drop it Hamilton's like Aaron Burr.
So, what folks may not know, because they're not elderly like me, is that you can put in
multiple entries to publish this clearinghouse sweepstakes on their website every day for
free.
You just have to scroll through a bunch of ads.
And so this may be a slight overshare, but I generally do this in the morning and the
bathroom on my phone.
But I don't actually think I'm going to win a large sum of money.
Like it'd be cool to win $10 million or $5,000 a week for life, but it ain't going to
happen.
Right.
And I don't go.
and do the entire, I do that to waste time because I got five bucks a couple of times.
Why not?
Right?
I'm not doing it because I seriously think and I'm putting some kind of hope investment
in receiving this kind of money.
There are folks who have been bamboozled by grifters like Benny Hinn and they're giving
Him money in the hope
that they're going to really magically not so much miraculously is magically have
money show up in their bank accounts or somehow get some kind of help.
They've been told to really believe that's true and then if it doesn't happen it's
because you didn't believe it hard enough.
And I blame, you know, the grifter obviously.
I don't so much blame the person.
The person has been caught up in a trend in modern life that really has a lot of its roots
in Freud, who through Freudian psychology that's filtered down to all of us has sort of
redefined what a human being is to a human being being a desiring thing.
It's just a thing that has desires.
If you've read any LeCon, those desires are always unmet.
They can never be met.
So having defined ourselves in this way and understanding ourselves is these desiring
things.
We have all of these things that we want, that we desire.
those desires and the futile quest.
to fulfill them, just drives us through our whole lives.
And if we stop and think, we think about
what are the things I think of as problems
in my life? What are the things I complain about?
What are the things I think would
fix everything if I just had or just this happened
than everything would be perfect.
Pretty much every case, it's some desire I have that isn't met.
But I think that if it were met, if it could just be met, then everything would be fine.
The problem is this unfulfilled desire.
And that unfulfilled desire, and I'm seeing it as our problem, inevitably twists and distorts
us in different ways.
to a lot of especially young men in our culture, the desire for sex, or in some cases,
a little more wholesomely, the desire for marriage, for having a woman to be a partner
a companion in their life, a wife, that desire not being met.
twist them until they turn into some kind of weird goblin on the internet.
There are people whose resentment of not having as much money and not having
the material things they think they deserve. Twist them, destroys their
relationships, destroys marriages, destroys families.
There are people who so desire success, being looked at in a certain way.
way. They pursue their careers and offer their families up on the altar of success. No
matter how hard we pursue any of those things, in fact the harder we pursue a lot of them,
the more we realize that we're always going to be lacking and that's never going to be
fulfilled. And what that makes is it makes...
one of the gifts of the Holy Spirit, one of the things we can only truly find through
Christ, it makes it a superpower. That's contentment. And our current world contentment
is a superpower. Contentment sets you free. Because contentment is
having all your desires fulfilled.
Contentment involves experiencing the lack,
experiencing the fact that there are all these desires you have that are
unfulfilled, but being at peace with it,
being at peace with it, that peace brings freedom.
And 10 minutes something we have to practice.
It's like patience.
We have to practice it over and over and over again and we get better at it.
Meaning we would get more and more at peace with not having everything,
with not always gratifying our desires.
That peace grows over time.
And because our society is so oriented the other way,
Let me tell you when you try to practice contentment.
No one will understand it.
You will not be praised for it.
If you start to practice contentment, you will be called unambitious, unmotivated, lazy.
Right. Something wrong with you that you're just content to live like that.
Right.
But the people who will say that those things about you are the people who are still enslaved
by their drives and desires that they're still out there in that futile quest of fulfill.
So seeing you living another way will sort of confuse them, maybe even frighten them.
And maybe they're wasting their life because they kind of are.
So while I'm not disagreeing with Father Andrew about repentance being the opposite of magic,
I think if we practice contentment, we get serious about it, about practicing contentment,
about being at peace with the things we lack.
In being at peace with the gifts that we have and the gifts we don't,
it peace with where God has put us.
life and the life that God has given us. Maybe even experiencing some joy over all those things.
If we practice that, we won't feel any need for magical thinking.
We won't feel the need to engage in any esoteric secrets or anything else.
to try to chase after fulfilling those needs.
But again, that contentment and that peace can only come through Christ, because that's
the place we can rest.
We can rest because there's nothing else we have to achieve.
There's no desire of ours that has to be fulfilled.
We can be free to do good to love.
When you don't need anything from anyone else, you're free to give to all of them.
That's what actual freedom, enjoy and peace in the Christian life look like.
That's my anti-magic rant.
It was less ranty than I was earlier.
Amen.
That is our show for tonight.
Thank you very much.
everyone for listening. If you didn't happen to contact us live, we'd like to
hear from you. You can email us at LordofSpirits.nationfeet.com. You can
message us through our Facebook page. You can also leave us a voicemail at
SpeakPipe.com slash LordofSpirits. And if you have basic questions about
Orthodox Christianity or you need help to find a parish head over to
Orthodoxintro.org. Join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth
Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific. Winter nights we sang
in tune played in
inside the months of moon.
Never think of neither, never let this spell last forever.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page,
you can join our very active discussion group,
leave reviews and ratings in the appropriate places,
and please share this show with a friend.
And finally be sure to go to www.extrapate.com
stroke support and help make sure we and lots of
other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
She had me spellbound in the night,
dancing shadows and firelight.
Thank you, good night.
May God bless you.
I keep you.
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders.
The number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands, seeing with a-
loud voice worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches and
wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5
verses 11 through 12.
St. Porferios told a story one time. He said, imagine you are in the desert and
you see a man being attacked by a tiger. What should you do? Would you throw a rock
Fuck at v-
a man? Of course not. But then he said, that's exactly what we do a lot of times when
someone is mean to us. We don't realize that they're being attacked by the devil, and
that's why they're being mean. Instead of being loving, we get angry at the person.
And this way the devil hurts him and then we hurt him some more.
Jesus?
for gave others, and his disciples are supposed to do that too.
I'm Father Alexis, and remember Christ is in our midst.
Love of money is the worship of idols, a daughter of unbelief, an excuse for
infirmities of foreboding.
old age, a harbinger of drought, a herald of hunger. He who has conquered this
passion has cut out care, but he who is bound by it never attains a pure
prayer. Poverty is a resignation of cares, life without anxiety, an unencumbered
traveler, alienation from sorrow, fidelity to the commandments. St. John
on Clemacus on Ancient Faith Radio.
Do not hold a loop from the church, for nothing is stronger than the church.
The church is thy hope, thy salvation and
Thy refuge, Saint John Chrysostom on Ancient Faith Radio.
came into the
world to save sinners. Therefore you came to save Me also. You came to find and to
save Him who was lost. Therefore you came to seek Me too, for I am one of the lost.
O Lord, O my God and Creator, I should have come to You as a transgressor of Your law.
I should have fallen at Your feet, cast myself down before You, humbly begging forgiveness,
pleading with you and craving your mercy.
But you yourself have come to me, wretched and good for nothing servant that I am.
My Lord has come to me, His enemy in apostate, My master has come, and has bestowed His love
of mankind upon me.
Listen my soul, God has come to us.
St. T. Con of the Danseq, an ancient faith radio.
I speak not of such a fast as most persons keep, but of real fasting, not merely abstinence
from meats but from sins as well.
For the nature of a fast is such that it does not suffice to deliver those who practice
it unless it is done according to a suitable law.
so that when we have gone through the label.
of fasting, we do not lose the crown of fasting. We must understand how, and in what manner
it is necessary, to conduct the business, since the Pharisee also fasted, but afterward
went away empty and destitute of the fruit of fasting.
The publican did not fast, and yet he was accepted in preference to him who had fasted,
In order that you may learn that fasting is unprofitable, unless all...
all other duties accompany it.
Fasting is a medicine, but like all medicines, though it would be very profitable to the person
who knows how to use it, it frequently becomes useless and even harmful in the hands of
him who is unskilledful in its use.
I have said these things not that we may disparage fasting, but that we may honor fasting.
the honor of fasting consists not in abstinence from.
food but in withdrawing from sinful practices. Since he who limits his fasting only to abstinence
from meats is one who especially disparages fasting.
Daily readings from the writings of St. John Chrysostom.
Hi, I'm Alisa Bielotic Davis, host of the Sunday Night Live Call-in Show, Everyday Orthodox.
My programs are a little unique among the other AFR live show offerings because I focus on
average Orthodox Christians who nevertheless have a profound impact on their parishes,
their families and their communities.
It's so inspiring to hear how God works in the lives of normal everyday people and I love
sharing their stories with you.
Most likely, you're also an everyday Orthodox sojourner who's striving to serve the Lord
and small and assuming way.
Did you know that you're the same sort of person who keeps ancient faith radio running and programs like mine on the air?
It's true. AFR is entirely sustained by ordinary listeners who express their appreciation for the station through humble monetary gifts of $50 or $100.
Sometimes even just $5 or $10. Every little bit helps. And without such support, ancient faith radio would cease to exist.
Would you?
Please take a moment right now to add your contribution to those of the other faithful
AFR fans who hope keeps such shows as everyday orthodox on the air.
It's an easy process.
Just go to ancientface.com and click on Donate in the upper right hand corner.
Be a participant.
Be a partner.
Become an ancient faith radio donor today.
Thanks in advance for your generosity.
The Lord has given us many councils and commandments to help us toward salvation.
He has even given us a pattern of prayer instructing us on how we are to pray.
He has given us life, and with his accustomed generosity, he has also taught us how to
pray.
made it easy for us to be heard as we pray to the Father and words taught us by the
Son. Let us pray as God our Master has taught us to ask the Father and words His Son has
given us to let Him hear the words of Christ ringing in His ears is to make our prayers
one of friendship, a family prayer.
St. Cyprian on Agent Face Radio
But let no one believe that fasting alone is sufficient.
For the Lord tells us by the mouth of the prophet, the kind of fasting I want is this.
the chains of
oppression and the yoke of injustice and let the oppressed go free.
And then continues, share your food with the hungry and open your homes to the homeless
poor.
Give clothes to those who have nothing to wear and do not refuse to help your own relatives.
The Lord therefore blesses the fast which uplifts our hands and almsgiving before His
eye which is joined to the love of our neighbor and founded on compassion.
That which you deny yourself give to another, so that that by which your body is weakened
may nurture the body of your hungry neighbor.
St. Gregory the Great on Ancient Faith Radio.